<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kathy Rose Astrology</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</description>
    <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://y7kim.github.io/rose/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 10:58:02 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Mar 2017 10:58:02 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Astrology of Pregnancy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/215-TMArose.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
by Kathy Rose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float:left; width:25%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/preganancy2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;What do you say to a woman
who asks you to look at her
horoscope to see if a pregnancy
is in her future? Often stressed
and anxious, she inquires emotionally,
“Will I have a baby? And if so, when?”&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, as astrologers, we want to be
able to answer these questions. We are motivated
to identify if and when a pregnancy
may occur, as suggested by reliable planetary
cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The astrology patterns present in a
mother’s chart for the nine-month period of
her pregnancy are both fascinating and complex.
However, the same aspects in a woman’s
chart that suggest pregnancy could also
point to many other things. We can’t know
for sure when a cycle will set the stage for a
new life coming forth or, instead, manifest as
personal expansion in another area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It would be nice and neat if there were
a magic formula (astrologically speaking)
that would allow us to be able to predict
pregnancy. But this just isn’t how astrology
works — at least, not in modern times when
we have more free will, more choice in this
regard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However intriguing it might be to identify
the planetary indicators that could suggest
pregnancy, I think it’s essential that we
approach this subject with both wisdom and
caution. As astrologers, we bear a responsibility
to be careful with our words and to be
respectful of the possibility that, when certain
thoughts are planted in a person’s mind, they
can manifest. Stress, fear, worry, and doubt
have such a strong effect on a woman’s hormonal
system that we certainly don’t want
to inadvertently plant a negative seed by not being mindful of how we address this
delicate topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact, though, is that women frequently
do come to an astrologer with
questions about conception and pregnancy
— wanting to know if and when
a child may come into their life. Often,
by the time they seek the counsel of an
astrologer, they’re already feeling anxiety
or pressure about this subject. This
is normal, and we need to know how to
handle this situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Free Will and Choice&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we start to look for potential
signs of an upcoming pregnancy,
we must first make sure that we understand
the reality of the person seeking
answers. We need to remember that reliable
birth control is readily available in
our culture, and women generally have
a great deal of choice with their reproductive
systems. While the ideal “textbook”
lineup of aspects for fertility may
be present in a client’s chart during her
childbearing years, she may choose not
to go in that direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why I always ask one or
more key questions: “Are you thinking
of pregnancy? Are you in a serious relationship?
Are you taking birth control?
Do you want a child?” In other words,
is a pregnancy a reasonable possibility,
given the client’s reality?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s important to remember
that planets don’t do things — people
do. Choice enters into the picture. The
astrologer who makes a dramatic and
declarative pronouncement, such as,
“You will be pregnant in July!” seems to
me to be acting out of ego, rather than
truly being of service to the client. Free
will needs to be honored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I saw a new client who had
been told by a psychic that she would
absolutely, positively be pregnant in February
2014. The client mentioned that
this declaration triggered a sense of fate
— a feeling that her pregnancy was out
of her control — as if it were ordained to
happen. Interestingly, it also intensified
her inner anxiety: She wondered if she
was doing everything “right” in order to
support the prediction. She actually worried
about missing the most fertile days
for engaging in sex, due to scheduling
issues with her husband’s work. A very
real fear arose because she focused on
not messing up the special time that was
so firmly forecast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;February arrived and she was not
pregnant … and still isn’t. She told me
she felt that she had failed, that she had
missed the window opened by the Universe.
She said she would rather not
have had the prediction issued.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This client had allowed someone
else to unduly influence her reality,
and this ignited a host of very stressful
feelings. The internal fear and anxiety
about fulfilling the prediction may
well have put her hormonal system into
overdrive, which could have contributed
to her not becoming pregnant. The
body–mind connection is so powerful!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many astrologers simply won’t issue
this type of exact or absolute prediction.
However, in my 30 years of consulting
with clients, I have heard plenty of stories
of damaging proclamations such as
this — stories that underline the need for
astrologers to be mindful and sensitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, I’ll explore the aspects
and references that suggest a potential
pregnancy, and I’ll present several
case studies that help us to understand
patterns. As you’ll see, the astrology of
pregnancy is a profound and fascinating
subject, one that calls for a clear awareness
that helps us to better serve our clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
Before we start to look
for potential signs of an
upcoming pregnancy, we
must first make sure that we
understand the reality of the
person seeking answers.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;The Trigger&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is always a good backstory
behind each article I write. Invariably,
an event or a trigger launches my interest
and leads to research, analysis, and
deep learning. This article started with
my preparation to speak at the annual
Student Seminar for the Noel Tyl Master
Certification Course, January 2014, in
Newark, New Jersey. Noel has given me
the opportunity to be his Teaching Associate,
and I was presenting a section on
the topic of planets moving to the Aries
Point (AP) by solar arc.1&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I was preparing for my lecture, I
let my intuitive mind guide me to celebrity
horoscopes that had planets at the
AP by solar arc so that I could use them
as examples. When I saw Chelsea Clinton’s
name in my files, I instantly had
the special inner nudge that signals me
to check out her chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, when I examined
young Ms. Clinton’s horoscope (see
&lt;b&gt;Chart 1&lt;/b&gt;, page 34), I saw that solar arc
(SA) Uranus was at 29°16’ Sagittarius in
January 2014. Uranus would solar arc
to the Aries Point (0° cardinal) later in
the year, in October. What I found interesting
is that, in her natal chart, Uranus
rules the 4th house, and when a
planet that rules an angle in the natal
chart moves by solar arc to the AP, there
seems to be an extra power to this kind
of “bloom.” So, I asked myself, “What
would be happening in her life with
4th-house matters, i.e., family issues?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking deeper in her horoscope,
I noticed that she also had SA Pluto =
(natal) Uranus (with solar arc notation,
we delete the aspect and insert an equal
sign) and SA Venus = Uranus in June
2014. It’s easy to see a repeating message
about the 4th house being highly
activated! I immediately started to wonder
about pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to all the activity with
Uranus in Chelsea Clinton’s chart, there
was also transiting Saturn conjunct her
Ascendant from November 2013 to
July 2014. The conjunction of Saturn
with the Ascendant is highly significant
and suggests the start of a new 29-year
cycle related to identity and sense of
self. There is almost always a major shift
in how we see ourselves with this cycle,
and we know that when a woman has
her first baby, there is a powerful change
in identity!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more measurement sealed
the deal for me: I noticed that transiting
Jupiter would conjoin her Leo Moon
in August 2014, and then square her
Ascendant from October 2014 to June
2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt that all this activity was a natural
signal for potential family expansion
and that chances were good that
we might hear an announcement of her
pregnancy sometime in 2014. I mentioned
this to the Tyl students in January,
and then on March 13, I also posted my prediction on Noel’s public Discussion
Forum in the section “Astrology of
the Famous and Well Known.”2&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On April 17, just one month after
my public post, we received the happy
news that Chelsea Clinton was indeed
pregnant, and she subsequently gave
birth to a daughter on September 26,
2014 — just six days before SA Uranus
moved precisely to 0°00’ Capricorn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The catalysts for this article and
the accompanying research were the
many personal e-mails I received in
response to my post on the Tyl forum.
I began to get requests from astrologers
who wanted to better understand
the cycles and aspects that may suggest
pregnancy. They were keen to have discussion
that went beyond the type of
thinking that “a transit to a planet in the
5th house will bring a pregnancy.” They
were intrigued by the measurements I
presented, which not only suggested a
pregnancy, but also resulted in one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I, too, wanted to delve more deeply
into the topic, so I began
to scour my files for
mothers and
their children. Thus began the process
of data collection for the cycles that
were going on when the women were
carrying babies in their bellies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/TAOP_Chart1.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:95%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Research Parameters&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I gathered data for 56 births from
36 mothers. In all cases except one, the
birth time is verified by the birth certificate.
I have personally worked with
most of the mothers for many years in
astrology consultations, and am familiar
with their life stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt that it was necessary to keep
the measurements simple and basic. My
belief is that the important, powerful life
changes are usually obvious and easy
to see in the horoscope, if you know
what to look for. My friend and mentor
Noel Tyl calls them big bells — they
vibrate loudly and attract our attention.
So, I looked only for transits from
Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune, and
Pluto, and I included just the aspects of
conjunctions, squares, and oppositions
to the natal planets, lunar nodes, and
angles in the horoscope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also looked for solar arcs, but only
the conjunctions, squares,
and oppositions. I
included solar
arcs to the
nodal axis and also solar arcs from the
nodes. Noel Tyl has advanced the idea
that the nodes can be a strong symbol
of female energy. Planets in the natal
chart that are configured with the nodal
axis often suggest the relationship with
the mother or significant female figure,
so naturally I extended that to include
motherhood. It made sense to me that,
during pregnancy, we might see transits
or solar arcs involving the nodal axis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might wonder why I didn’t
include the harmonious trine or the
flowing sextile aspects. My feeling is that
these easy measurements don’t propel
us forward with enough significant
momentum or a strong enough push
to result in a major life change. I have
always found that the aspects that have
tension produce the biggest growth and
forward movement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used charts of women who had
birth times verified by their birth certificate,
with only one exception: the chart of
my mother-in-law. Her story of pregnancy
is very interesting, and I will use her chart
as an example to illustrate my point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the women included in this
research had more than one child, and
a few had as many as four. I looked
at the transits and solar arcs that were
going on during the nine-month period
of their pregnancies. This is a simple
thing to do: You take the date when
the child was born and count backward
nine months, and then you scan that
time frame for the transits and solar arcs
in the mother’s chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My focus was not to find the exact
time of conception, but rather to look at
the entire period of pregnancy. I watched
for the outer-planet transits that made
an exact contact during that nine-month
period. I did the same with solar arcs:
I considered only the arcs that came to
perfection while the woman was carrying
the baby, or at the time of birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the research for this article
by asking myself the question: &lt;i&gt;“What
patterns would you anticipate seeing
in a woman’s horoscope at the time of
pregnancy?”&lt;/i&gt; I thought I’d see frequent
traditional fertility solar arcs involving
the Sun and Venus, or Venus and the
Ascendant, and so on. I also assumed
that there would be a predominant pattern
of transits or solar arcs to the ruler
of the 5th house or to planets in the 5th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;My belief is that the important, powerful life
changes are usually obvious
and easy to see in the
horoscope, if you know
what to look for.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this didn’t show up with as
much regularity as I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I anticipated seeing didn’t
prove to be the case. I was absolutely
fascinated!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Giving Birth Is a Big Life Event&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I considered that I may have been
thinking in terms that were too narrow
regarding the astrology of pregnancy.
Conceiving, growing a new life, and
having a baby represent a huge lifestyle
change — it is a significant and powerful
life-altering event when a child is
brought into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most women these days are
engaged in careers and continue to
work even after having a baby. A hundred
years ago — maybe even 50 years
ago — this was not common. In the
early 20th century, most women viewed
getting married, having babies, and raising
a family as their primary life purpose
and career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of charts I used for
research were those of women born in
the 1940s or ’50s — the point in time
when their childbearing years coincided
with the more widespread acceptance
of women in the workforce. The database
for this article contains a few charts
of mothers who were born in the early
1900s and also several who were born
in the late 1980s and early ’90s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it’s important to reiterate
that, early in the 20th century, becoming
a mother was linked to the sense of
achieving one’s life purpose. Unless one
was in the über-wealthy upper class and
could afford a full-time nanny, women
stayed home, and their entire focus was
on raising their children and managing
the household. Perhaps if we exclusively
studied horoscopes for births in
the 1800s and early 1900s, we may see
a different pattern, compared to what I
saw with contemporary births.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern times, women focus
their ambition and desire for achievement
not just on having a family, but
also on a career. Having a baby is certainly
significant, but — let’s be real —
nowadays when a woman who works
full time has a baby, her life assumes a
high degree of complexity as she juggles
a career and childcare issues. This
also adds responsibility to the father’s
lifestyle, but the stress felt by the man is
more often one of financial pressure to
provide security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We still hear many stories suggesting
that, despite both parents working
full time, it’s usually the woman who
does the majority of cleaning, cooking,
and household caretaking. I know there
are exceptions, but it seems that career
women are now taking on two full-time
jobs when they have a baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how would all this show up
in the horoscope? Isn’t it reasonable
that the cycles that are present in the
chart of a woman who becomes pregnant
would symbolize a big life change
instead of just fertility or 5th-house
references?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;The Data&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I analyzed the charts, I found it
very interesting that there were consistently
three to five different big bell transits
or solar arcs going on simultaneously
during the pregnancy. In many cases,
there were even more than five. This is
likely the most noteworthy piece of information
to consider. We should probably
change the way we are viewing this,
moving from “What specific transits or
solar arcs suggest a birth?” to “How
many cycles are occurring at once when
a woman becomes pregnant?” With this
approach, I began to expect to see three
or more major cycles going on simultaneously
in the chart of a pregnant mother,
as I continued to collect the data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following is a breakdown of aspects
for the 56 births I analyzed (from 36
mothers with accurate birth data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;1. Angular Activity&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most frequent cycle I saw was a
transit from an outer planet — or a solar
arc — to an angle, with the Ascendant
and Descendant having the most activity.
Twenty-six charts out of 56 (46%)
received direct hits to these angles. Four
of those charts had more than one transit
or solar arc affecting the Asc./Desc. at
the same time. Jupiter and Saturn cycles
hitting the 1st/7th axis were most common.
Interestingly, Neptune followed a
close second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The direct hit to an angle is certainly
significant, and we should keep
this in mind when we are pondering
the question of a potential pregnancy
(major life event). Angles are the most
dynamic points in the horoscope, so we
can expect powerful movement in life
when one of these areas is contacted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The most frequent cycle
I saw was an outer-planet
transit or a solar arc to an
angle, with the Ascendant
and Descendant having
the most activity.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as potent for change and
growth is the planetary ruler of an angle
being activated by a transit or solar arc.
Since Mercury and Venus each rule
two signs, there are more opportunities
for an angle ruler to be triggered, so I
didn’t tally up the number of charts that
reflected this. But I must mention that
the angles were the most active areas
by far, receiving the most hits in the 56
births I studied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Angles and their rulers must be considered
as power generators for major
life changes when activated by transits
and solar arcs — and this activation
was consistently present in the charts of
pregnant women in my research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;2. The Sun&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-two out of 56 pregnancies
(39%) had exact contact from a solar arc or an outer-planet transit to the natal
Sun, with eight of those charts showing
multiple transits or solar arcs to the Sun
going on at the same time. Again, as with
the angles, Jupiter and Saturn cycles to
the Sun were most common, with Neptune
following a very close second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Sun is the symbol for our core
sense of self, our life purpose and direction.
Strong transits and solar arcs to
the Sun offer us a period to consider a
course correction in life, to build a new
feeling of confidence, or to strengthen
our identity. Often when the Sun is activated
by a cycle, we re-evaluate who we
are and where we are going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes sense that cycles to the
natal Sun would be a consistent pattern
for pregnant women. When a woman
carries a pregnancy to term, there is
often a change in how she sees herself.
I’ve had frequent conversations
with women who mention that, when
they become a mother, it’s very common
for them to refer to themselves as
“someone’s mom” instead
of using their own
name. The inner image shifts to mother
and protector of a child, rather than
the image of oneself as a separate
individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One note about Neptune transits
or solar arcs showing up frequently
both to the angles and to the Sun: At
first this really surprised me. I certainly
never anticipated Neptune as being a
factor in a pregnancy! However, when
we consider that there is enormous sacrifice
required when a woman becomes
a mother, isn’t that Neptune energy?
And there’s the issue of the temporary
change (loss) in individualized identity
that happens for women when they step
into the powerful role of guardianship
and protector of new life. Mothers tend
to put their children’s needs first; there
is often a selflessness that goes with the
job. Neptune frequently dissolves ego,
and this fits in with the bloom of motherhood.
Interesting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;A Miracle Birth:&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jupiter Hits the Sun
The only horoscope I included
that does not have a verified birth time
is that of my mother-in-law, Emma
Rose. (I use a sunrise chart when no
time is provided.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mrs. Rose very much wanted to
have a large family and began trying
to become pregnant in her early 20s,
right after she got married. Following
many years of focusing on getting pregnant
with no success, she finally went
to a doctor for help. She was told that
she was infertile, and was absolutely
crushed. However, as is occasionally the
case, Mrs. Rose was shocked, amazed,
and thrilled when, out of the blue, she
became pregnant at 39 years of age. In
the 1950s, that was considered very old
to have a first child. She always referred
to her son, my husband, as her “miracle
baby.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought of her story when I started
this article, and knew that I had to check
out what was going on in her chart
during her pregnancy. (See &lt;b&gt;Chart 2&lt;/b&gt;, at
left.) I anticipated seeing either a Venus
solar arc or a contact from Jupiter, simply
because that carries the “miracle”
energy. Amazingly, when she became
pregnant, it was during SA Jupiter =
Sun. She was also receiving a transit
from Jupiter in Aries to her natal Jupiter
and Venus in the fall of 1951, when she
discovered she was pregnant. Miracle
baby, indeed! The benefic rays of Jupiter
produced the reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One last note about this horoscope:
Mrs. Rose suffered from frequent
migraine headaches, but when
she became pregnant, they stopped
completely — probably due to the
hormonal changes. She mentioned to
me many times that, during the nine
months of pregnancy, she felt the best
she ever had in all her life. Again, we
see the benefic Jupiter solar arc shining
through!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/TAOP_Chart2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:95%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suspect that we’d see activity to
her angles, if we had her birth time.
She lived a long and fulfilling life, passing
away when she was 93. I felt that
chances would be good that, even without
a birth time, the aspects reflecting
the miracle pregnancy would be easy to
see — and they were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;The Moon is a natural symbol
for the mother energy,
and it’s normal to anticipate
that it might receive transits
or solar arcs when a woman
becomes pregnant.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;3. The Moon&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Moon is a natural symbol for
the mother energy, and it’s normal to
anticipate that it might receive transits
or solar arcs when a woman becomes
pregnant. Twenty-one out of my 56
research horoscopes (37%) had examples
of the Moon being transited or contacted
by a solar arc, with 6 of those
21 having multiple cycles to the Moon
during pregnancy. Interestingly, contact
from Uranus to the Moon was strongest,
followed by Saturn, Pluto, Neptune, and
then Jupiter, in that order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I had a powerful theme
of lunar involvement for both of my
pregnancies. Transiting Uranus was
square my Moon when I was pregnant
with my first baby, and with my second
child I had SA Pluto = Moon and transiting
Jupiter opposite my Moon happening
at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also had SA Ascendant at 0° Cancer
(Aries Point, or AP) when I gave
birth to my first child. This is especially
significant because I never thought I
would want children. I have a very independent
warrior Moon in Aries. Having
my SA Ascendant hit the AP in Cancer,
a lunar-ruled sign — along with the Uranus
transit to my Moon — totally altered
my thinking, and I embraced motherhood
with a passion! My identity easily
flowed into the role of nurturing mother
and caretaker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;A Surprise Pregnancy:
Uranus Transit to the Moon&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my long-term clients, “Pam”
(a pseudonym), was totally astonished
when she became pregnant with her
first child at age 45. She had an amazingly
easy pregnancy and gave birth to
a healthy son when she was just three
months shy of her 46th birthday. (See
&lt;b&gt;Chart 3&lt;/b&gt;, below.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Pam became pregnant, she
was in a long-term serious relationship
but wasn’t married. The surprise
pregnancy pushed her and her partner
to wed immediately, and the cycles
going on in her chart at the time tell the
tale. We see the “surprise” by the many
cycles involving Uranus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transiting (TR) Uranus conjunct
the Moon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA Uranus = Mars
(ruler of the 4th house)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;TR Saturn conjunct Uranus
(exact two months after the birth)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA Uranus = Jupiter (ruler of the
Ascendant)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;SA Midheaven = Uranus&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The repeating pattern of contact
through transits and solar arcs in her
chart (both to Uranus and from Uranus)
suggests the sudden and unexpected
change that the news of pregnancy
brought into her life. With the Uranus–
Moon transit, plus the solar arc from
Uranus to the ruler of the Ascendant,
we see the powerful trigger to an angle,
which I mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s fascinating that, in a consultation
Pam and I had in 2005, I mentioned to
her that there was a suggestion of marriage
or perhaps significant relationship
development in her chart in 2006. I saw
this with SA Venus = Sun, which was
exact in mid 2006. Because I never even
considered that pregnancy might occur
(given the fact that she was in her mid
40s), I naturally thought of marriage or
relationship issues instead. The marriage
did manifest, but it was triggered
by the fact that she became
pregnant!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ll explore the Venus energy
next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/TAOP_Chart3.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:95%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;4. Venus&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I stated earlier, I anticipated seeing
a predominance of Venus cycles in
examples of pregnancies because I associate
this planet with matters of women’s
fertility. From the sample charts I had,
37% were receiving a transit or solar arc
to natal Venus. Particularly interesting to
me was that there were 21 charts with
Venus being aspected; in 5 of the 21,
Venus ruled the 5th house (children),
and another 5 of the 21 had Venus ruling
the 4th (family).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, it was Saturn transits
or solar arcs to Venus that were most
common (6 cases out of 21), followed
by Pluto (5 cases), Uranus (4 cases),
and Jupiter and Neptune (2 each). The
cycles I usually consider to be classic
potential pregnancy indicators are either
SA Venus = Ascendant or SA Ascendant
= Venus. There were 2 cases
of each of these cycles in
the sample.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me share with you a clear case
example that had Venus and Ascendant
activity: Veronica is a client of mine who
also became one of my astrology students.
Her studies, however, were interrupted
by her pregnancy. What’s truly
wonderful is that Veronica allowed the
class to use her chart in early 2012 as
a teaching tool for aspects that suggest
a possible pregnancy. Starting in late
2011, she began to feel the desire to be
a mother tugging at her, and in January
2012, she asked if we could explore this
topic in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Veronica has one of the very easyto-
spot signatures for heightened fertility.
(See &lt;b&gt;Chart 4&lt;/b&gt;, below) When she
asked the question about possible pregnancy,
she had SA Ascendant at 27°55’
Virgo. I noticed that she would have SA
Asc. = Venus exact in the fall of 2012
(solar arc planets advance forward
5 minutes of arc per month). She also
had transiting Pluto square her natal
Jupiter–Saturn conjunction (Jupiter is
the ruler of the 5th house). I knew that,
in the summer of 2012, transiting Uranus
would join the mix in opposition
to natal Jupiter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all I needed to see to feel
confident in saying there was a strong
suggestion that it probably wouldn’t be
difficult for her to conceive sometime in
2012. I felt very comfortable saying this
because she had already announced
her intention. I never told her she would
conceive — I mentioned that there was
a suggestion of easy conception. I think
that putting it this way sends a better
message and doesn’t create pressure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She became pregnant in the spring
of 2012, just before transiting Jupiter
was conjunct her Midheaven, and gave
birth in December.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;I hope you spotted something in
Veronica’s horoscope suggesting a second
child: Did you see that SA Sun =
Venus (Midheaven ruler) in 2016, exact
in December 2016?&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to mention something noteworthy
here: Veronica has the luxury
of living circumstances where she does
not need to work. She is viewing motherhood
as her career and a large part
of her life purpose, and she is a very
happy, dedicated, full-time mother. Perhaps
this is why one of the old “classic”
signatures — Venus combined with the
Ascendant or Sun — was present during
her first pregnancy (with the theme
showing up again for possibly another
baby in 2016).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;5. Jupiter&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were 18 out of 56 pregnancies
in the research group (32%) where
natal Jupiter received a transit or solar
arc. In 8 of these 18 cases, Jupiter ruled
either the 4th or 5th house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jupiter return was in play for 5
of the pregnancies — that was the most
active cycle. For the solar arcs, a few of
the planetary combinations that really
make sense with birth were present:
Ascendant = Jupiter, Sun = Jupiter,
and Moon = Jupiter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/TAOP_Chart4.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:95%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;6. Saturn&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twenty-one pregnancies (37.5%)
had a solar arc or transit to Saturn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most frequent questions
I received from astrologers, after
my posting on the Tyl forum, concerned
the Saturn transit conjunct Chelsea Clinton’s
Ascendant, and whether the Saturn
energy would make the pregnancy
difficult. Honestly, at first I also contemplated
this, until I collected enough data
and questioned many of the mothers
who had this aspect. I learned that very
few of them mentioned difficulty while
they carried or delivered their baby.
Perhaps the consistent Saturn cycles
that show up are simply pointing to the
fact that the structure of our daily life
changes when we bring in a new life.
Having a child is a serious matter, really
an issue of increased responsibility —
and isn’t this the essential message from
the Taskmaster planet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;7. Uranus&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thirty percent of pregnant women
in my research group were experiencing
an exact transit or solar arc to Uranus.
There were 17 cases with natal Uranus
activated, and 3 of those were receiving
multiple cycles to that planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to note that Saturn transits
to Uranus were most common. This
makes sense when you consider that
the Saturn–Uranus combo spells change
and the release of the old so that fresh,
new energy can come in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;8. Nodal Axis&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m very glad that I included the
transits and solar arcs to the nodal axis
because, in 30% of the pregnancies,
there was an exact transit or solar arc to
the nodes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transiting Jupiter to the nodal axis
showed up most frequently. I did not differentiate
between the North and South
Node, but simply looked for contact to
either. I also recorded how many times I
saw the SA nodes hitting a natal planet,
and there were 6 cases out of 56.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transits and solar arcs to the
nodal axis shouldn’t be ignored. I understand
that considering “motherhood” as
a symbol when the nodes are activated
may be a new concept, but the fact
that it happened in 30% of the cases is
extremely interesting. This subject needs
more study, of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;9. Neptune&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sixteen cases out of 56 (28%) had
a direct hit to natal Neptune through
solar arc or transit. In 4 of those cases,
there were multiple cycles triggering
Neptune.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Transits from Pluto to Neptune
were the most common; however, this
is largely because all but one of the
women in my sample had Pluto and
Neptune in sextile in the natal chart,
and Pluto had moved to transit Neptune
during the childbearing years. Jupiter’s
transits to Neptune were almost as frequent
as Pluto’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;10. Pluto&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transits or solar arcs to Pluto were
present in 25% of the cases I studied.
The very powerful transit from Saturn
to Pluto was most common. That was a
surprise because this cycle is connected
with hard work and sometimes loss. I
wouldn’t have anticipated seeing these
two planets in contact with any regularity
during a pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Summary&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suggest that you consider your
analysis and understanding of planetary
activity related to the astrology of pregnancy
this way: The cycles work in combination
with each other and create an
active time frame in a woman’s life for a
major life event. No single cycle stands
out that would herald a pregnancy in
and of itself. Instead, you need to be
aware of multiple big bell aspects chiming
together. It then seems logical that a
concurrence of planetary cycles can trigger
this kind of momentous expansion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When analyzing the horoscope
of a woman in childbearing years, we
should be alert to the time frames when
the chart is highly activated by many
solar arcs or transits occurring at once
— and especially take note if the angles
are involved. We must also be practical:
With effective contraception so
prevalent, if a woman is practicing birth
control and has no intention of getting
pregnant, the patterns I am presenting
will likely bring about a result other than
pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve already started a new level of
research with the women in this study,
asking them to describe significant
events going on in their lives and their
state of mind when they became pregnant.
As we would expect, their stories
flow with the specific transits or solar
arcs that were in effect in their chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And of course, this topic wouldn’t
be complete without pondering the
activity that was going on in the father’s
horoscope during the period of the
mother’s pregnancy. Future research will
bring this critical context to the discussion
of the astrology of pregnancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The learning continues …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Chart Data and Sources&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(in order of appearance)
&lt;b&gt;Chelsea Clinton&lt;/b&gt;, February 27, 1980; 11:24
p.m. CST; Little Rock, AR, USA (34°N45’,
92°W17’); A: letter from the White House.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Emma Rose&lt;/b&gt;, August 9, 1913; time unknown
(sunrise used); Nashville, TN, USA (36°N10’,
86°W47’); X: date without a birth time.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;“Pam,”&lt;/b&gt; December 23, 1960; 6:19 a.m. PST;
Los Angeles, CA, USA (34°N03’, &lt;br /&gt;118°W15’);
AA: birth certificate.
&lt;b&gt;Veronica&lt;/b&gt;, August 17, 1981; 6:48 a.m. EDT;
Norfolk, VA, USA (36°N51’, 76°W17’): AA: birth
certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;References and Notes&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The Aries Point is 0° of the cardinal signs
Aries, Cancer, Libra, and Capricorn. See my
article, “The Aries Point Bloom,” in The Mountain
Astrologer, Aug./Sept. 2013.
&lt;li&gt; http://noeltyl.com/


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;i&gt;© 2015 Kathy Rose – all rights reserved&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/KathyRose2.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:25%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;br clear=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;

&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kathy Rose&lt;/b&gt; is an astrologer with an international
clientele. She is a Highest Honors
Graduate of Noel
Tyl’s Master’s Degree
Certification Course
in Astrology and
also serves as Tyl’s
Teaching Associate.
Kathy is also the producer
and publisher
of the 9-part Tyl
MasterWork DVD
series, and has developed
an appreciative
audience with her popular YouTube channel
(roseastrology), featuring more than 100 videos.
To contact her, telephone: (757) 340-5516;
e-mail: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:roseastrology@yahoo.com&quot;&gt;roseastrology@yahoo.com&lt;/a&gt;; or visit her website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://roseastrology.com&quot;&gt;http://roseastrology.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;

&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/215-TMArose.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 09 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/09/TheAstrologyOfPregnancy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/09/TheAstrologyOfPregnancy/</guid>
        
        <category>none</category>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Embracing the Adventure of a Uranus Cycle</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The following article was published in The Mountain Astrologer Magazine.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float:left; width:20%; margin:8px 15px 5px 0px;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/AquarFbook.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Have you ever experienced a small electric shock, giving you that sharp jolt of energy that causes you to jump? No doubt you have. You know how it energizes your senses and snaps your attention fully into the moment, so that you’re completely aware and alert. That sudden, shocking surprise triggers a sensorial rush, while your adrenaline surges because of the zap coming out of the blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We feel a similar thrill when we ride a roller coaster — especially when we’re riding it for the first time, and we don’t know the track’s course. In this thrill of adventure, there is an “in the moment” awareness as we deal with sharp turns, sudden steep drops, and upside-down spins through breathtaking 360-degree loops. The special excitement, the tingling sensation we feel, comes from the sensory stimulation and even the sense of danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Electric shocks and roller-coaster rides are akin to Uranus cycles you may experience. Surprise, sudden change, and unexpected jolts are common during one of these powerful transits or solar arcs. We move into a primal awareness of the present moment when this happens, our natural tendencies kick in, and we respond with quick reflexes. Our reactions often bypass our intellect and spring instead from our instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you ready to embrace the adventure, harness the energy and “ride” your Uranus cycle to higher spiritual ground?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What Do Uranus Cycles Teach Us?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s examine the spiritual purpose and potentially profound impact of a Uranus transit or solar arc. What is our opportunity for expansion and personal evolution? How can we use a Uranus cycle for maximum development and growth on the soul level?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of a Uranus cycle is to break up stagnation, plain and simple. The energy from Uranus throws symbolic bolts of lightning that use a sudden burst of shocking “spiritual electricity” to shatter what is crystallized and loosen what is stuck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another analogy is the jackhammer that tears apart concrete by using rapid, powerful bursts of irresistible force. Or dynamite that explodes, blowing up whatever is static or “stuck”. We could also include the “spark” to the dead battery in our car that jumper cables offer. This jolt of electricity gets things moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to remember this purpose — breaking up stagnation — because sometimes, when we’re in the middle of a disruptive Uranus cycle, we lose sight of the fact that there is actually a benefit to all this upheaval. The unexpected change that these cycles bring can often be emotionally jarring, but nonetheless helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prominent British astrologer and author Alan Leo called Uranus the “Awakener” planet. And indeed it is, often causing us to awaken with a start. When crystallization is shattered, a new pattern can be created. Often, we don’t see this until the old way is broken apart. We are awakened to a new way of seeing and doing things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uranus cycles can also trigger feelings of restlessness and a desire for freedom and adventure. Once we release what we’ve outgrown, we feel liberated. We are able to move forward through life, traveling light instead of dragging heavy baggage behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expect, and Accept, the Unexpected&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a Uranus transit or solar arc comes knocking on our door, it’s often demanding and unrelenting, like the raven in the poem of the same name by Edgar Allan Poe. The better part of wisdom here is to willingly surrender to the fact that our routine will be disrupted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some people respond better than others to this frequency, this cyclic wave of change. Cardinal signs are usually willing to spring into action — wanting to do something when the unexpected surges into their life. Mutable signs often relax into the flow — exhibiting the flexibility that comes naturally to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fixed signs are most prone to digging in their heels and resisting. (Imagine dragging a scared dog by the leash into the veterinarian’s office.) Their need for repetition and routine makes Uranus cycles particularly challenging for them. The change is brought on too abruptly, too quickly. Fixed signs need time to warm up to a new direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being a big fan of J. R. R. Tolkien, I’m reminded of his classic creation, The Hobbit — wherein the wizard Gandalf pulls Bilbo Baggins of the Shire into an adventure that forever changes Bilbo’s life of routine and repetition. Bilbo resembles someone with a fixed sign, such as the Sun. The Hobbit is firmly attached to habit, secure in the comfort and familiarity it offers. He is initially resistant to Gandalf’s invitation to adventure, protesting, “We are plain, quiet folk, and I have no use for adventures. Nasty disturbing uncomfortable things! Make you late for dinner! I can’t think what anybody sees in them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gandalf doesn’t give up with Bilbo’s first rejection. He urges again, with Bilbo snapping, “We don’t want any adventures here, thank you!” Still not giving up, Gandalf finally says, “I will go so far as to send you on this adventure. Very amusing for me, very good for you — and profitable too, very likely, if you ever get over it.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bilbo, not understanding that he really has no choice in the matter, responds in the negative one last time, “Sorry! I don’t want any adventures, thank you. Not today. Good morning!” Gandalf then scratches a symbol on Bilbo’s door, and the very next day unexpected guests start to arrive — the inevitable adventure begins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because Bilbo is forced out of his predictable routine —the stale and stagnant pattern in his life — he grows significantly as an individual. He is awakened to his inner potential and tremendous capacity to deal successfully with the unexpected. The little Hobbit learns that he is capable of far more than he realized. He steps into the spontaneous, the unknown, the challenging … and he flourishes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This example, where Gandalf is the symbolic agent of disruption and change, mirrors a Uranus transit. We will often react as Bilbo did when our secure routine is threatened, and this is particularly so with fixed signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Immovable, Meet Irresistible&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients, Cheryl, has a Taurus Sun and Midheaven (MC). In 1999, when Uranus was in Aquarius and formed a square to her Sun and MC, she went through a period where she realized that her career was not fulfilling. She was on a dead-end path with little opportunity for growth, and this area of her life seemed stagnant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheryl started to feel the Uranus vibes of restless change a few months before the first contact, but didn’t want to quit her job. She felt huge emotional resistance to making a change. She preferred to stick with what was known, instead of venturing out into the unknown, despite the troubling sense of stagnation she was feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Uranus, the planet of Awakening, made the first direct connection to her Sun, Cheryl suddenly lost her job. BAM! The first lightning bolt from Uranus was thrown. She was shocked and spent the first few months of the transit almost in a state of denial as she wrestled with her Taurean need for security and her tendency to want things to remain the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a few months, Cheryl was ready to make a slight life adjustment. She emotionally opened up enough (out of necessity) to apply for positions through a temp agency. She knew she needed more time to fully embrace a new career direction, and doing temp work would buy her a little breathing room. However, the idea of a job being only temporary really bothered her — her nature, her need, was to build something lasting!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately upon opening to the possibilities, Cheryl began getting temp positions — each one having specific ending dates that she was given in advance. This triggered a new sort of trauma to her comfort zone, her sense of security: What would happen after the job ended? Would another opportunity come up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In each situation, Cheryl would find a new position either on the very last day of a temp job or during the week right after the position ended. She had to wait till the last minute before the new opportunity would appear. At first, this was extremely stressful and nerve-wracking. Her nature was oriented to having a solid plan and something she could count on. It took her many months before she learned to relax into the uncertainty and to trust that when she needed something, it would be there for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This ability to relax into the unknown was a big breakthrough for my client. I remember her excitement when she realized that she really could handle change and uncertainty with becoming overly emotional. Cheryl had confronted a critical issue deep within her, one that had always held her back. She also tuned into the frequency of trust and the ability to handle temporary situations. 
This awakening of capability allowed her to explore a new direction in her career, something she was unwilling to consider before the transit. And you know what? That new direction proved to be more rewarding and satisfying than she could have imagined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheryl moved from a low paying dead end job to a new career where she feels stimulated, challenged, and appreciated. She was able to embrace the unknown and seek a position in a PR firm. She has been offered leadership positions and has increased her income considerably. Thank you, Uranus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resistance Is Futile&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most often during a Uranus transit, we will experience three exact “hits,” and this “tri-cycle” usually lasts about a year. Depending on how entrenched we are in our routine, the first hit is sometimes met with inner opposition. During the second contact, we may still resist, but the change has already started and pressure is building. The status quo has been challenged, and there is a need to start responding. The final hit necessitates the release of our resistance, our blockage, and demands action. Now we must deal with the change and grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solar arc from Uranus will be strongest when the aspect is exact, but we need to remember that there is a slow buildup of energy starting six months before, and a gradual release over the following six months. Generally, we can say that the solar arc is active for about a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Temporary Zone:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staying in the Moment&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a Uranus cycle, we are thrust into a period of time when we live in a “temporary zone.” The transitional period (temporary zone) is felt most deeply when our Sun, Moon, or one of the angles in our horoscope receives a strong aspect (conjunction, semi-square, square, opposition, sesquiquadrate,) from Uranus. It’s so common to hear people who are in the middle of one of these cycles say, “For now, what I’m doing feels right, but I know it’s only temporary. I don’t know what’s next.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The challenge is to handle this with grace and to stay open to the instructions from the Universe. One way I communicate this to clients is by saying, “Keep your engine in neutral — just idle until you get the ‘spark’ to move forward. Then shift into ‘drive’ and step on the gas.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a Uranus adventure, we are required to move to a new level of instant obedience when we get the signal to “act.” We are given no warning about when the ideas for the new direction will come. Out of the blue, we’ll be hit with a lightning bolt of inspiration, and the next step on our path will suddenly be revealed. When we receive the flash of illumination, we need to allow ourselves to respond quickly. There is an almost magical sense of perfect timing brought on from a Uranus cycle when we trust and act instantly. This is part of the adventure of spontaneous growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not many cultures focus on the value of being “in the moment.” Certainly, we see athletes learning to master this type of consciousness — they must be fully present so that they can react instantly and respond to the unexpected in a game situation. They live in a state of perpetual readiness with quick reflexes — always prepared to make the adjustment that the moment requires.
I learned this when I was involved in martial arts, especially when we would spar. At the time, I had a chronic shoulder problem — very little force would cause it to dislocate. We did full contact sparring; we had padding, but that didn’t completely protect us from injuries or from the pain from a powerful kick or punch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Korean master didn’t know what to do with me. I was a woman with intense drive and a passion to learn and compete, and I showed enormous enthusiasm. Consequently, he would match me with very tall and heavy men when we sparred, which always gave them the advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to confront quite a bit of fear every single time I entered the ring. Not only did I have to protect my shoulder, but I also faced an opponent who was bigger and stronger. Out of necessity, I learned to drop my energy into my belly and focus completely in the moment. I worked on trusting that I would be able to handle whatever happened. Believe me, it was not easy! I had many painful and shocking sparring rounds in the ring before I figured this out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I did make the shift in consciousness — and could completely bring my attention and focus into the competition at hand — I did well. It was powerful and impacted me tremendously. I learned on a deeply physical level that when I was fully present — with all my senses alive, alert, and aware — I stepped into an intense flow of energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Isn’t it interesting that I started my martial arts training just as transiting Uranus was approaching a square to my Sun, and I got my black belt when solar arc Uranus moved to the Aries point? My perspective on life and my approach to it changed because of my martial arts training, which was triggered by a Uranus transit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Uranus Buzz&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some common but surprising physical side effects of a Uranus cycle. The high electrical energy from this planet sometimes manifests as a jittery, almost super-caffeinated feeling. This is most common when it’s a transit or solar arc to the Sun, Moon, Mercury, or Ascendant. I frequently hear clients mention that they have a hard time getting to sleep because they feel wound up and wired. When this happens, I always recommend consistent extra exercise to help burn off some of the excess energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people experience so much electricity coursing through the body during this cycle that they frequently burn out lightbulbs, short out appliances or drain the batteries in their watches. In these situations, gardening and contact with the earth can help, as there is a need to ground the electricity. Soaking in a tub of epsom salts will also offer relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also mention to my clients that it’s beneficial to keep a pad of paper or a small digital recorder near them at all times when they are going through a Uranus cycle. It’s common to have a brilliant, innovative idea pop in — like a lightbulb suddenly turned on by the planet’s electric charge. So often, if the idea is not written down or recorded, the details quickly fade and are lost. We need to embrace inventive energy and relish the “outside the box” thinking that the energy of this planet stimulates, and we need to be ready to bring it into form by taking action when we get the signal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a warrior’s focus and simplicity with Uranus energy. We can harness the electricity from this planet when we remember these key points:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be mindful of the power we tap into when we fully engage in the present moment.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear our minds and emotions of unnecessary fear, worry, and chatter and focus on the situation at hand.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stay open to receive. Trust that answers will always arrive exactly when they are needed.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Embrace spontaneity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we willingly move into adventure mode, a new confidence starts to bloom. Our attitude and behavior shift into knowing we can handle the unexpected, because we step into full awareness of the now. This allows us to be free, to be liberated, to be shed of the false security of the predictable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the gift of Uranus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/08/EmbracingUranus/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/08/EmbracingUranus/</guid>
        
        <category>none</category>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Navigating through the Neptune Fog</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;published in the Mountain Astrologer&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float:left; width:20%; margin:8px 15px 5px 0px;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/Pisces2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
Have you ever become assertive and energized when talking about Mars transits? Or wild and adventurous when discussing Uranus? When you look at your own horoscope cycles or those of your clients, does your behavior begin to resonate with the planetary signature energies?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what happens to me. I physically and emotionally feel, and often manifest, the frequency of the planet involved in a transit or solar arc, especially when I’m trying to describe a significant upcoming cycle for a client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, when I talk about Saturn, I become more serious. My speech pattern slows, my consciousness aligns with perseverance, discipline, structure, and order. With Pluto, I step into the primal energies of death and rebirth, moving into the trusting frame of mind that is required with the transformative process connected to this cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This remarkable resonance has worked well for me, with the glaring exception of the energy associated with one planet - Neptune! Until recently, I’ve had a difficult time describing what I felt when I tune into the nebulous energy from this mystical giant. The spacey and foggy feelings would tend to confuse me, and I would lose the words to convey my message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A telling example of this is my experience in writing this article. As I sat down to write, I would think about Neptune, connecting and tuning into its vibrational energy. Within moments, I would find that I was losing my train of thought, adrift in a right-brained fog. I stared at the computer screen, lost in ethereal abstraction instead of purposefully moving forward with organized expression. I spent many hours simply trying to clear my head long enough to write a coherent sentence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I compare that to how I wrote my last article, which was about Aries energy. Staying focused on the speedy, dynamic Martian frequencies of Aries caused my fingers to fly across the keyboard. My thoughts came fast and furious. For that article, my challenge was to keep up with the words racing through my head.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always understood that Neptune is associated with abstract spiritual vibrations that are often hard to put into words. In fact, when I compare Neptune to Saturn, I typically use the example of comparing the texture of silk to burlap. Saturn’s frequency is rough and coarse, like burlap; Neptune seems smooth and delicate, like silk. Saturn is much easier to grasp and explain - the energy impact is so very practical and mundane. Neptune’s energy impact, on the other hand, is elusive and insubstantial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m sure this experience is due to my particular learning style and the fact that I have no planets in air in my chart. I learn through experience - through touching, feeling, and seeing. For me to be an effective counseling astrologer, I first need to have a tangible sensory experience with a cycle in order to explain it well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, in the last two years, I have had a breakthrough with sensing and understanding the Neptune vibration. I had the one-two punch of overlapping cycles from this mystical planet - a powerful solar arc from Neptune to my natal Saturn and a transit to my natal Mars. I’d like to share my clarifying experience with you, in the hope that it may help you to see better through the mist when you are in a Neptune cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;A Visit from Neptune&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My journey of enlightenment with this mystical planet began in the spring of 2007, when transiting Neptune squared my Mars (see Chart 1). I knew this would be a significant transit, because Mars is a key planet for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mars, the Warrior Planet, sits in the 12th house in my chart, just 5 degrees from my Ascendant. My identity is closely aligned with the highly focused, even stubborn determination associated with Mars in Taurus. I’ve lived most of my life feeling inspired by challenge and nourished by aggressively facing anything that attempts to stop me from achieving my goals. My approach to life is direct, immediate, and to the point. Vigorous exercise is like fine food to me - I love the warrior energy and thoroughly enjoy feeling strong, powerful, and in command.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as Neptune was approaching the square to my Mars by transit, imagine my surprise when my usually fearless approach to life began to change. Instead of being energized by challenge, I started to feel indifferent and sometimes even overwhelmed. Where I would normally want to prove myself against the odds - eager to push past obstacles - I instead began to turn away and look for an easier, less demanding path. It was as though I had an energy leak. At first, this change was subtle and gradual - sneaking up on me like a stealthy opponent - then becoming very powerful during the first hit of the transit in March 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;The One-Two Punch&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In June 2007, a few months after the first hit of the Neptune square Mars transit, solar arc Neptune conjoined my Saturn. [1] (See Chart 2,) It was the overlap of a solar arc and a transit that accelerated everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important: The one-two punch of an overlapping solar arc and transit must be given serious consideration when analyzing a chart. This usually signifies a pivotal developmental period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life began to change very quickly with the two cycles working together. The solar arc of Neptune to Saturn started to dissolve my comfortable, orderly, and disciplined reality. I found that it became more difficult to muster passion and enthusiasm to achieve personal goals, resulting in a horrible feeling of being unproductive. Self-doubt started to creep in, along with a certain level of inertia. I felt as though I had lost all my initiative, as well as my sense of purpose and organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to admit that there were times when I viewed myself with a degree of self-loathing, during this initial energetic shift. I felt that I had lost control of my sense of direction and was wandering aimlessly, buffeted by circumstances. I began to wonder where “the real me” had gone. I asked countless times, “Who is this woman inhabiting my body? I don’t know her. Where did I go?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When late summer came, I noticed that my normal ambition and desire for achievement had totally dissolved. I had to really push myself to stay on track and get work done. To my horror, even my house - my disciplined refuge - became messy and disorganized. I just couldn’t seem to keep up with everything like I normally did, and stark feelings of failure started to emerge. It became more and more difficult for me to find my gutsy confidence and determined drive; fear and self-doubt began to rear their ugly heads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Neptune and Ego Wipeout&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our understanding of Neptune is that it has a finely tuned high frequency that is not necessarily congruent with life’s practical, mundane realities. During a Neptune cycle, aggressive impulses are softened, the drive to achieve loses steam, and the urge for competitive challenge slowly dissipates. While we are in one of these cycles, it is often more difficult to stay grounded and to engage in practical tasks. Instead, our energy wants to align with vague idealism, peace, and beauty. Imagination and intuition are often heightened. It’s as though the influence from this planet helps to create a bridge to abstractly philosophical, artistic, and spiritual worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout his work and lectures, Noel Tyl presented the idea that Neptune cycles can easily signal “ego wipeout.” I could so fully identify with the personal sense of wipeout that I decided to call him when I was feeling particularly bewildered and frustrated. I wanted to discuss how I could transform this foggy period into a purposeful, productive time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my talk with Noel, he mentioned that there is a reason for the wipeout: It creates an opportunity for personal regrouping and rebuilding. He continued by saying that, for someone who is naturally oriented to spirituality or aesthetic pursuits, it can also be a time of great creativity and inspiration - if the doors are open to those things. He asked me, “Are your doors open?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the perfect question! I realized that, instead of surrendering and flowing with the Neptune vibes, I was full of resistance, and my doors were not open. Instead, I had slammed them shut, trying to keep out this new and uncomfortably abstract energy. Plunging into the Neptunian fog scared me. It felt so nonlinear and formless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is a very common reaction to Neptune transits, especially for type A personalities. Learning how to adjust to and proceed with the dreamy and ethereal approach to life can be challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Opening the Doors to Creativity&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as I faced the fact that I was full of resistance and apprehension, I could form a plan for making a meaningful change, which enabled me to connect with Mars again. I had my challenge defined. I knew I had to relax, let go, move with the energy, and find out where it wanted to take me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I practiced staying loose and relaxed, not focusing judgment on myself and my unfamiliar reactions. I meditated more frequently and allowed myself to drift and have spaced-out moments. I started to pay attention for messages or guidance, when I ventured into the abstraction. I made a sacred pact that I would not sink into downward-spiraling self-criticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was difficult. My basic nature wanted to drive forward and forcefully break through the hazy mist. I was very impatient to get back to work in my usual way. However, when I tried to force productivity, I noticed that my confusion would increase - once again, a clear signal that forcing was not the right approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I surrendered, I quickly noticed that new creative desires and avenues were opening for me. I began to feel waves of artistic energy flowing into my consciousness. There were times when my hands would literally shake with creative anticipation. I felt an incredible yearning and urgency to express myself, to explore colors, textures, and shapes. One day, I finally gave in to the urge and sat down with markers and colored pencils and let the creativity pour onto paper. How exciting! Several hours later, I had produced my first mandala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Making Friends with Neptune&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I started to let the art flow, it wouldn’t stop. I would create for days on end. I noticed that making mandalas satisfied my need to have order and organization, even in my art. Mandalas are concentric layers of geometric shapes arranged symmetrically. Their structured symmetry perfectly resonates with the orderly energy of Saturn. This was an ideal expression of the solar arc of Neptune to my Saturn!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mandalas are rhythmically beautiful and are designed as meditation pieces, gently inviting you to pause and reflect. Frequently, people comment on how a mandala can hold their attention for long periods of time. They mention that they feel that they are being pulled into the piece, as if they are entering a vortex. This type of art is not static; there is constant energetic motion, always moving toward the center point. The spiritual effect is a clear representation of Neptune. Mandalas structure and organize energetic patterns in aesthetic terms: Saturn and Neptune working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started to put my work in a few small art shows, it became clear to me that each mandala I made was intended for a specific person. The process I went through in making the piece represented what was going on in that person’s life in retrospect. For instance, sometimes I would struggle to find the right colors and shapes - tearing apart my creation countless times, building and rebuilding. The mandalas that were the most difficult to birth would always find an owner who had just gone through a similar process in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I surrendered to the creative flow, the faster everything developed. I engaged my pioneering Mars and bravely experimented with new materials, using layers of cut paper in my pieces - adding metal, fabric, beads, and wood for a three- dimensional effect. I found that it was difficult and sometimes overwhelming to keep up with the images in my head. They would flood my dreams and waking state. I felt saturated with abstraction and creativity - not overwhelmed, rather overjoyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Neptunian vibrations sensitized me to the frequencies of colors. I began to hear color combinations as music. When the perfect blend of shades came together in a piece, a beautiful chord would sound. If I introduced a color that wasn’t right, I would hear a cacophony of uncomfortably discordant notes. I knew, at this point, that I had fully entered into the Neptune reality, and it was clear to me that my natal Mars was responding beautifully to this planet’s aesthetic energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Random Acts of Kindness and Selfless Acts of Beauty&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working for the benefit of others is also very much connected to Neptune. I knew this intellectually, but I wasn’t prepared for the waves of charitable inspirations that started to flow through me. I was intensely involved with the practice of yoga during my Neptune cycle. (It’s no surprise that I was drawn to a more spiritual form of exercise at that time.) Yoga helped to clear my channels, opening me to better receive the spiritual frequencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often, during yoga classes, I would be filled with incredibly inspired ideas for how to help some of the people in my life. These would come as full visions with complete details. Without hesitation, I began to take action on these thoughts. I knew that this was the direction in which I had to move.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea was to create a fundraising event for a local dance company with which my daughter dances. The vision was so complete and comprehensive that I was able to put it together in a few short months, raising much-needed funds that allowed the dancers to continue their performances. It was so successful that it has now become an annual event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also decided to start marketing a friend of mine who is a wonderful spiritual artist. This woman has always needed a manager. She’s supremely gifted as an artist but lacking in the business end of things. I arranged for her to paint a giant mural at my children’s school and got her into a few large art shows. This launched her in a new direction, giving her enormous exposure and a welcome push.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2007 and 2008, I can say that a good portion of my time and energy went to fundraising and charity work. My schedule was extremely busy, and I juggled many projects at once - all for the benefit of other people. I felt completely nourished and fulfilled as I actively worked to help others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As long as I moved with the flow and focused on art and charity work, I was able to maintain direction and accomplish my chosen tasks. It became clear to me that, in the beginning of the cycle, I felt so fuzzy and bewildered because I wasn’t responding positively to the Neptunian nudges. A new direction was trying to manifest. All I needed to do was to open the door and let the inspiration flow through, to guide me along my new path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My life has changed for the better because of this cycle. I am now selling my art regularly, which has nicely supplemented my income. Because of my charity and fundraising work and the connections I’ve made, I’ve been invited to participate in several art shows, which was an unexpected personal benefit of my efforts. Even though my entrance into the realm of Neptune wasn’t very graceful at first, it all worked out for the best. My experience with this planet has taught me so much and has expanded my astrological vision as well as my career.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We always strive to recognize and receive the benefits from transits and solar arcs. These cycles are ultimately opportunities for spiritual and personal growth. However, when powerful outer-planet transits and solar arcs first present themselves, there are also often difficult side effects that we must understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our success with any cycle depends on how well we adjust to the new frequency. As with any transit or solar arc, we must remember that the planets are not doing anything to us; rather, we are responding to the planetary frequencies. We have a certain level of choice in how we respond to and use the vibrations in which we are being bathed during a major cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neptune can act like a tranquilizer; its energy can make you feel dopey and “out of it,” with little to no motivation. Now that I am up to speed with “Neptune-talk,” I am able to warn my clients and educate them about the possible uncomfortable, even distressing side effects of these cycles. Conveying this requires some skill; otherwise, you run the risk of programming a negative reaction and creating fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is far too easy to foster the mindset in a client to expect a bad experience. Word choice is critical, along with a reminder that we have free will and choices. We may struggle more with cycles from some planets than others - just as I had a hard time initially adjusting to the Neptune energies - but that does not mean we should throw up our hands and declare that the experience will be horrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is helpful and important to maintain an attitude that approaches a planetary cycle with the expectation of good. Remembering to focus on converting the new energy into positive action allows us to respond purposefully to the cycle, instead of just reacting blindly out of fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many benefits to be derived from Neptune cycles. Just as Noel Tyl said, they can be a time of great creativity and inspiration. Even as I write this, I’m heading into another long transit from this ethereal planet. Soon, it will square my Ascendant/Descendant and then my Sun and Venus. I can’t afford to sit in dread of the fog moving in and once again shrouding me in confusion. Instead, I’ve chosen to view this as a wonderful opportunity for soul growth, greater self-awareness, and hopefully more artistic, spiritual, and intuitive development. My recent experience has prepared me to open the doors and not fear the fog, trusting that I will find my way through the mist.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/07/NavigatingNeptune/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/07/NavigatingNeptune/</guid>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Midpoint Madness and the Orlando Massacre</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bonus Content Article for TMA Subscribers — Aug./Sept. 2016 Issue&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/816TMARoseBC.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;by Kathy Rose&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic mass shooting that recently stunned Orlando, Florida and the rest of the
United States — as well as impacting people in far parts of the world — is still producing shock
waves of sadness and grief for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very mindful of the negative effect on our energy field when there is constant focus
on such a tragedy, disaster, or catastrophe. So, my intention with this article is not to continue to
amplify feelings of distress but rather to focus on a meaningful learning opportunity — looking
through the clarifying lens of astrology. In particular, I would like to point out a potent
midpoint pattern involving Mars, Saturn, and Pluto combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s take a look at the natal chart of the man identified as the shooter inside the
Pulse nightclub, Omar Mateen. (See &lt;b&gt;Chart 1&lt;/b&gt;, below.) Mateen has a stellium in Scorpio falling in
the 5th house, including the Sun, Mercury retrograde, and Venus retrograde tightly conjunct
Pluto. At first glance, we are instantly able to understand that the shooter was fueled by
emotional energy, and that much of this fixed water intensity is internalized (due to the two
personal planets being retrograde) — supercharged and empowered by the Pluto conjunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been my experience that, when Venus is retrograde in the natal chart, we must
consider an undercurrent of developmental tension, related to social expression and
relationship needs, as an influential part of the person’s life purpose. The degree to which this
may manifest as problematic depends on the complete view of the patterns present in the
horoscope — and of course, on the choices the person makes regarding how to express the natal
energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mateen’s chart — with Pluto conjunct retrograde Venus, which rules the 5th house
(giving and expressing love) — there is a suggestion of challenge and intensity related to the
social and emotional dynamic. So often, Pluto conjunct a personal planet adds “extremes” to the
mix, and here we could say that there is an overabundance of internalized, highly emotional
relationship energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natal Mercury retrograde pulls energy inward even more; in Scorpio, the intellectual
process flows from deep feeling and emotion instead of from objective logic. The planet that
symbolizes &lt;i&gt;how a person needs to think and communicate&lt;/i&gt; is internalized and repressed. And since
Mercury is in Scorpio, the thought process could easily move into secretive, clandestine, covert
patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/mateenChart.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite often, when the two inner personal planets are retrograde, we see a second agenda
swirling under the surface, unknown to others. Symbolically, we could say that Mateen’s 5th
house is similar to an inner emotional volcano, aggressively — even obsessively — churning
beneath the surface with powerful, intensified, and eruptive emotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions reflected in Mateen’s 5th house are reinforced by Mars in Aquarius, ruling
the 11th, in a tight square to the Sun. The energy of giving and receiving love (5th–11th axis) is
powerfully challenged. One more echo of deep hidden emotions is the natal Moon at 29°+ Taurus in the 12th house, opposing the Sun and squaring Mars. A dynamic t-square is formed
that demands our attention when we view this horoscope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing to look at the relationship and sexual energy in the shooter’s natal chart, we
must observe that Neptune is conjunct the Descendant. Neptune on an angle can suggest
unclear energy: &lt;i&gt;“Something is other than it seems.”&lt;/i&gt; There is often confusion or bewilderment that
needs to be worked through as part of the life path, and in this case, it flows into relationships.
Another echo with this same theme is natal Saturn (ruling the 7th and 8th houses) square
Jupiter in Neptune-ruled Pisces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see a repeating pattern with the planets that rule the houses connected with
sexuality, intimacy, and relationships (5th, 7th, 8th) all involved with challenging aspects.
Again, this suggests that clarifying emotional needs regarding sexuality and relationships is
very much part of the life purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many news accounts of Mateen’s supposed friends and acquaintances
who came forward and said they felt that he may have been gay. We know that there was
conflict with his religious views — he has been described as a practicing Muslim — and the
issue of whether his alleged homosexuality would be rejected by that community. Mateen
reportedly embraced a radicalized, extreme view of Islam, which projects intense criticism and
condemnation of a lifestyle that is not heterosexual. The symbolism of Neptune on the 7thhouse
cusp is concomitant with the need to hide sexual desires that were not supported by the
important people in his life and the religious views to which he subscribed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mateen’s chart, there is a clear and powerful statement that sexual and relationship
energy was severely challenged by high developmental tension as part of his life-purpose
theme, and we can assume that this played a part in the choice he made in the location of the
shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more could be said about his horoscope, but now let’s look at the midpoints and
other factors in both his chart and that of the shooting event. There are powerful repeating
patterns involving Mars, Saturn, and Pluto that make a dynamic statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Aries Point Activation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrific mass murder at the Orlando nightclub that catered to LGBT patrons took
place when an important and influential midpoint picture was formed by the transiting planets
at the Aries Point (AP): &lt;b&gt;AP = Saturn/Pluto&lt;/b&gt;. (See &lt;b&gt;Diagram 1&lt;/b&gt;, below. I use the 90° midpoint sort,
which places all the cardinal signs at 0°–29°, the fixed signs at 30°–59°, and the mutable signs at
60°–89°.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/orlandoShootings.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the chart for the event (Chart 2, following page), we can see that the
Aries Point (0° cardinal) was on the angles. I’ve written about the power of the AP before, and
how this zone in the zodiac carries a &lt;i&gt;public projection&lt;/i&gt; dynamic. As I first glanced at the event
chart, my eye naturally could see that the midpoint of transiting Saturn and Pluto that day was
at the AP. Pause for a moment and let that soak into your consciousness. Combine the symbols
of Saturn and Pluto with the AP. What do you feel? It’s a heavy, somber, serious public
statement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saturn/Pluto midpoint carries the most challenging energy of all the planetary
combinations, and on the day of the shooting, it was located at 29°38’ Sagittarius — just half a degree from being exactly on the 0° cardinal mark. We could interpret this as the &lt;i&gt;potential for loss
and destruction on a wide public scale&lt;/i&gt;. This powerful midpoint is made even more active because
in the event chart it falls on an angle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most investigators are now characterizing the shooting as an act of terrorism. The fact
that the midpoint energy of Saturn/Pluto was active at the AP is no surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/orlandoShootingChart.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Saturn and Neptune Connections&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of the event, Neptune and Saturn were exactly square. This is important
because Saturn in Sagittarius brings our awareness to religious issues and the potential for
righteous attachment to strict doctrine or dogma. Neptune in Pisces also calls our attention to
matters of faith&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current transiting Saturn–Neptune square had been activating Mateen’s natal
Saturn–Midheaven (MC) square. The shooter’s Saturn return was in full swing, pushing him to
make big life decisions — this is when we are urged to &lt;i&gt;grow up and pick our path&lt;/i&gt;. The potent
cycle at 29 years of age offers a major course correction, and we make choices about our
commitment to achievement. We know that when Saturn comes back to its natal position, there
is a push to move into a new level of maturity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the pressure from the Saturn return, I believe that the major trigger for
Mateen’s mental/emotional/psychological break was the transit from Neptune to his MC. The
first hit was in March 2016; the final contact would have been in early 2017. Neptune contacting
an angle by transit can offer a spiritual or artistic breakthrough, but it can also intensify
confusion and increase bewilderment, depending on what’s going on in the person’s life. The
increase in emotional distress or disorientation stemming from the Neptune transit may have
felt like a heavy, dense mist, obscuring and reducing the ability to see clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Mateen had homosexual feelings and was programmed to believe that those urges
were evil or sinful — possibly so sinful as to deny him salvation — the Saturn return and
transiting Neptune activation, plus transiting Mars about to station square his natal Mars,
would ignite motivation to do something to release the fog and become clear. He did indeed
make a choice, and it was deadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing to examine the midpoints in the event chart, we see more patterns that
reflect potential violence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Neptune = Mars/MC&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(confusion and idealism with assertive energy)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Saturn = Mars/MC&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(strategic public aggression, focused protest, or violence)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Mars/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(ego is illuminated through extreme passion, aggression, and force)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Neptune/ASC&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(ego identified with idealism or confusion, possible covert activity)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Saturn/MC&lt;/b&gt; — all are exact by degree! &lt;i&gt;(personal achievement through discipline and hard
work — the need to exert control)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the midpoints in the event chart accurately reflect the tragic action, and we
clearly see the repeating pattern with Mars, Saturn, and Pluto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Omar Mateen’s Natal Midpoints&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we move to a deeper look at the shooter’s natal midpoint picture (Diagram 2,
below), and we see the unmistakable pattern of three heavyweight planets again! Here are the
relevant midpoints in Mateen’s natal chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/mateenMidPoints.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mars = Saturn/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(assertive energy used to release frustration, fighting back with extreme force)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Saturn/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(achievement through hard work and discipline).&lt;/i&gt;This is very important to
consider, because transiting Mars in Scorpio was retrograding back to a conjunction with the
natal Sun, further igniting and triggering the killer’s aggressive tendencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;AP = Mars/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(extreme and forceful energy with public projection). &lt;/i&gt;What a sad thing — to
become famous (AP energy) for a horrible, historic act of extreme violence! This became his
legacy of infamy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Mateen’s Midpoints Activated by Transits&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natal midpoint activation by transiting planets or by Solar Arc directions is important to
consider. When I analyze triggers to key midpoints, I keep the orb very tight. I look for an exact
hit by degree, and the closer to the minute, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of the shooting, we see that the transiting AP = Saturn/Pluto triggered
Mateen’s natal AP = Mars/Pluto. This presents an amazing correlation with the potential for
violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pattern continues with transiting Pluto at 16°49’ Capricorn, igniting Mateen’s natal
Mars/Saturn midpoint, which is 17°01’ Capricorn &lt;i&gt;(assertive energy and discipline come together
with forceful projection — extreme anger and frustration)&lt;/i&gt;. This is again a very challenging and
difficult combination of energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transiting Sun at 21°42’ Gemini on the day of the shooting was illuminating and
energizing Mateen’s Saturn/Ascendant midpoint, which is 21°24’ Pisces &lt;i&gt;(personal achievement
through hard work and discipline)&lt;/i&gt;. The Sun also triggered his Mars/North Node midpoint &lt;i&gt;(public
aggression or protest)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there was an exact trigger from transiting Mercury to the natal
Uranus/Pluto midpoint — and also conjunct Mateen’s natal Moon &lt;i&gt;(intense thought activity and
emotion that overturns the status quo – agitated thinking)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more thing: Mateen’s MC and Saturn had moved by Solar Arc to exactly trigger his
natal Jupiter/Pluto midpoint &lt;i&gt;(strategic amplification of personal power)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again and again, we see the repeating pattern of Mars, Saturn, Pluto combinations
standing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Media outlets have said that Mateen yearned for a career in law enforcement. He had
applied to the police academy and had been rejected. Over a number of years, he had
reportedly taken and excelled at shooting courses. At the time of the murders, he was working
as a security guard at a gated residential community, which may have fulfilled some part of his
desire — or instead could have underscored a profound sense of underachievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the stellium in Scorpio and the midpoints illustrated earlier, this man was wired
to be interested in deep emotional intensity and, perhaps, life issues involving violence. With
appropriate love and support, he could have channeled this into being very skilled at detective
work, criminal investigation, general police work, or the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is always a choice as to how we use the energies present in our horoscope. Mateen
had the vocational profile for undercover police work, solving mysteries, and even confronting
violence. Somewhere along the way, he got off track, and a very negative manifestation of his
natal chart was chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite probable that his sexual feelings, which may have fueled his confusion, his selfdoubt,
even his rage — feelings in deep conflict with his religious views — helped push him to
make these unfortunate choices. An unresolvable emotional conundrum led to a downward
spiral that triggered the shadow and negative manifestations of all the aforementioned natal
energies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Spectrum of Expression&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I teach astrology, I frequently mention the importance of considering the concept
of &lt;i&gt;spectrum of expression&lt;/i&gt; regarding the natal chart. I believe that two people can be born on the
same day, at the same time and location, and yet express vastly different levels of the planetary
patterns in their natal chart. When we take physical form on the Earth plane, we bring with us
the strengths and vulnerabilities from other incarnations — based on how we’ve chosen to react
and process prior life experiences. It is my belief that we have choice every step of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the shooter had scheduled an astrology appointment prior to the horrific event, we
would certainly have made note of the obvious challenges and tensions in his horoscope in the
preparation for consultation. However, it is irresponsible to make an absolute judgment, prior
to talking to the client, as to whether these natal challenges might be expressed constructively or
destructively. We must communicate with our clients and listen for details that inform us how
they are living their chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is incredibly sad that Omar Mateen engaged his natal energies in such an
extreme, negative spectrum of expression. Our ethics as astrologers compel us to remember to
look at all levels of possible manifestation. I believe that we must consider the circumstances in
life development that are specific to the individual before making a declarative evaluation of
natal energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because a person has a stellium in Scorpio, with Venus retrograde conjunct Pluto,
doesn’t mean there will be powerful emotional or sexual conflict that intensifies and leads to tragedy or violence. The cookbook astrological approach of “this means that” tends to represent
only one tiny portion of possible expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this very troubled man and a terribly tragic event, we can work backward
and learn from the planetary patterns involving Mars, Saturn, and Pluto that were active that
day. We can absorb the meaningful challenges in Mateen’s natal chart so that we may be more
informed of the potential difficulties if we see similar patterns in our client’s horoscope. Our
goal is to be of service and to help others find a path to the most positive expression of the natal
chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must use this knowledge and awareness with wisdom, integrity, and humility. That
is the path of the astrologer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Chart Data and Sources&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Omar Mateen&lt;/b&gt;, November 16, 1986; 7:00 p.m. EST; Queens, NY, USA (40°N43’, 73°W52’); AA: birth
certificate published in The New York Times, June 19, 2016.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Orlando Shooting&lt;/b&gt;, June 12, 2016; 2:02 a.m. EDT; Orlando, FL, USA (28°N32’, 81°W23’); news sources
report that the first 911 call came in at 2:02 a.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
© 2016 Kathy Rose – all rights reserved&lt;br clear=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/KathyRose.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kathy Rose&lt;/b&gt; is an astrologer with an international clientele. She is a Highest Honors Graduate of Noel Tyl’s
Master’s Degree Certification Course in Astrology and serves as Tyl’s Teaching Associate. Kathy is also the
producer and publisher of the 9-part Tyl MasterWork DVD series, and has developed an appreciative audience
with her popular YouTube channel (roseastrology), featuring more than 100 videos. To contact her, telephone:
(757) 340-5516; e-mail: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:roseastrology@yahoo.com&quot;&gt;roseastrology@yahoo.com&lt;/a&gt;; or visit her website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://roseastrology.com&quot;&gt;http://roseastrology.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/816TMARoseBC.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/06/MidpointMadness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/06/MidpointMadness/</guid>
        
        <category>none</category>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Appreciating Aries Energy in Women</title>
        <description>&lt;img style=&quot;float:left; width:20%; margin:8px 15px 5px 0px;&quot; src=&#39;../../../../../img/articles/Aries.jpg&#39;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am a female with Moon in Aries. I also have a prominent Mars in Taurus, sitting right on the Ascendant in strong aspect to Jupiter and Uranus. I am highly attuned with and inclined to warrior energy, competition, independence and enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can I say that I always receive love and approval and appreciation for being a strong and gutsy woman? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have I had my share of moments when I questioned whether I should be more passive, less forceful and less impatient, more traditionally feminine? Absolutely!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do I realize that I used “I” eight times in the three previous paragraphs? Of course...with enthusiasm! (How very Aries-like!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, charge ahead with me and explore the struggles and challenges, as well as the opportunities for liberation and growth, that women with strong Aries energy often face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aries is the first sign in the zodiac - how wonderfully appropriate for those who relish being first. This fire sign is associated with leadership, independence and assertiveness. Ruled by Mars, Aries is raw, primal energy - instinctive, gritty, courageous and competitive. It is the warrior, the conqueror archetype - eager to face challenges and motivated to push to new levels of personal excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aries carries the vibration of “I am”. Self-discovery is the purpose inherent in this sign. Because of this, there is high emphasis on protecting one’s independence and self-reliance. This is expressed through quick reactions, elevated physical instinct and unrelenting competitive drive. Aries promotes a direct and to-the-point approach to life, charging forward fearlessly - always ready to lead and conquer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have Sun in Aries, you will resonate with this description. With the Sun, this dynamic and fiery Aries power fuels you and supplies you with the energy to express yourself boldly into the world. It is the spark that passionately drives and sustains your ego and sense of self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have Moon in Aries, the warrior and leadership vibrations are connected to your reigning needs and what you must do to feel nourished and fulfilled. You NEED to assert yourself and to be independent and courageous. You NEED to be a trailblazer and meet challenges head-on. (1) These actions and activities are necessary for you to have a sense of happiness, satisfaction and completion. Expressing yourself in this way is like consuming a gourmet meal for the soul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More often than not, these Martian energies work well if you are male. Bold and assertive men who exhibit high ambition to succeed or who have a strong drive for leadership are generally admired and rewarded. Society naturally embraces the heroic, competitive male paradigm. Men with Sun or Moon in Aries can find several male role models in history and myth who have positive connotations, like Sir Lancelot, Hercules and champion cyclist Lance Armstrong. For men, expressing the Mars-ruled Aries energy is uncomplicated and straightforward. This makes sense, as both Aries and Mars have masculine polarities. There is a natural affinity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However. if you are a woman and have Sun or Moon in Aries, there are fewer female warriors as examples or role models. Assertive women who are also competitive seem to receive more criticism and disapproval. Women who have strong opinions and are obviously ambitious or who operate in positions of authority are often referred to as “bossy”, “cold” or “pushy”. The Aries energy is not always as easy for a woman to embrace and express because it is in conflict with the gentle, nurturing sensitivity of traditional femininity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many women with strong Aries planets, including me, struggle with integrating and expressing their warrior nature. In my astrology practice, I frequently hear women clients say that they fear they’re being selfish, egotistical and self-centered when they are being assertive, ambitious and competitive. They worry that they will be judged and disliked - that when they exhibit the exact same behavior as men, it will be interpreted differently...and negatively. The social programming for women to sacrifice their needs and desires and to put others first is pervasive. Speaking up and directly asking for what you want is all-too-often not considered feminine.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;ARIES, MARS AND VENUS&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dr. Deborah Tannan wrote a brilliant book about the differences women and men have in their conditioning and programming, and how that affects their conversations with each other. What Dr. Tannen describes is the basic expression of Mars and Venus, the planets that symbolize masculinity and femininity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In her book, “You Just Don’t Understand”, (2) she mentions that women are not socialized in such a way that emphasizes competition; instead they focus on intimacy and connection. They are taught to cooperate instead of to compete. Their orientation (especially with each other) is linked to achieving a sense of community and support. They tend to minimize differences with one another and will avoid appearances of superiority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Men, on the other hand, are socialized in such a way that emphasizes independence, power and accomplishment. Status and hierarchy play a key role in men’s relationships. They are motivated by keeping the upper-hand and view many situations as a contest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On pages 43-44 of her book, Dr. Tannan asserts,“boys tend to play outside, in large groups that are hierarchically structured. Their groups have a leader who tells others what to do and how to do it, and resists doing what other boys propose. Boys’ games have winners and losers and elaborate systems of rules that are frequently the subjects of arguments. Finally, boys are frequently heard to boast of their skill and argue about who is best at what.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Girls, on the other hand, play in small groups or in pairs; the center of a girl’s social life is a best friend. Within the group, intimacy is key: Differentiation is measured by relative closeness. Many of their activities (such as playing house) do not have winners or losers. Though some girls are certainly more skilled than others, girls are expected not to boast about it, or show that they think they are better than the others. Girls don’t give orders; they express their preferences as suggestions, and suggestions are likely to be accepted. Whereas boys say, “Gimme that!’ and “Get outta here!” girls say, “Let’s do this,” and “How about doing that?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What has been taught and handed down through generations of social programming, makes it much more acceptable for a boy to express the pure energy of Mars, just as it is easier for a girl to gain approval by radiating the graceful, gentle, accommodating energy of Venus. Whether it’s ideal or fair is for another article; the fact is, masculinity is linked to Mars and femininity to Venus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Venus Mars&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;indirect and persuasive&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;direct and to-the-point&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;avoids appearance of superiority&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;heirarchical approach&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;cooperation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;competition&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;seeks community, support and rapport&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;motivated to keep the upperhand&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;works for consensus and closeness&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;will rise to a challenge&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;minimizes differences with each other&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;status orientation&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;desires intimacy and connection&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;preserves&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;independence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Former fashion model Tyra Banks (chart #1) has Moon and Mars in Aries and is described as having a straightforward approach to modeling with a spirited and vivacious personality. She was one of the first black fashion models to reach “supermodel” status, and the first black model to be on the covers of the Sports Illustrated Swimsuit Issue, GQ and the Victoria’s Secret catalog. Tyra admits to being very competitive, both with others and with herself - constantly pushing herself to new boundaries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortly after retiring from modeling, Banks used her strong Mars energy to fight back when tabloids turned on her, ridiculing her for some unflattering photos that were shot of her at bad angles after she had put on a few extra pounds. She defended herself in true Aries style by courageously coming out in her swimsuit on TV during her talk show, boldly demonstrating how even a supermodel’s body can look bad at certain angles. Her gutsy and feisty reaction to the critics landed her at the forefront of the debate of how skinny is too skinny, and how fat is too fat. She took an intense, challenging situation and dealt with it head-on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ellen Degeneres (chart #2) also has Moon in Aries and is another example of a strong and courageous woman. In 1997 (3) when she came out of the closet, she became television’s first openly gay superstar. She asserts that she didn’t do it for a political agenda - she did it because she needed to be genuine and to live her truth. Her independence continued to show when she was asked to host the Oscars and refused to wear a dress. She said, “I just don’t feel comfortable in a dress. I don’t want to apologize for who I am”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Tyra Banks and Ellen Degeneres have indeed had their share of criticism. Tyra has been called egotistical and self-absorbed by some - all because she knows what she wants and fearlessly goes after it. Ellen triggered quite a reaction when she boldly told the world about her sexual orientation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the most part, there is still the frequency of conflict surrounding a woman’s effort to step outside the social norm in expressing her femininity. Women who have a strong Mars or Aries quality in their horoscope have to learn to maneuver around these social hurdles in order to find full and satisfying expression of their nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In preparation for this article, I interviewed many women with either Sun, Moon or Mars in Aries. I asked them how they express their warrior energy and how they feel it is received. I specifically asked them if they ever engage in competition, and if they do, in what manner? I was curious to hear their feedback on how it is to be a woman with Mars-oriented femininity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the conversations I had, I found that it didn’t matter if the woman was a successful dynamo in the corporate world, or if she was a stay-at-home mom focusing on her family - they all had similar stories and feedback. The vast majority said that they frequently feel guilty about their competitive urges, as if having them were something to be ashamed of. In fact, many prefaced their stories with, “I’m embarrassed to say” or, “I’ve never really admitted this to anyone” or, “I know this makes me sound terrible”. I found it very interesting that again and again they would first apologize for having the strong desire to compete and to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A successful corporate executive - we’ll call her “Mary” - sent me a letter describing how she feels about her Moon in Aries. She wrote, “I have always expressed my Aries energy and I thoroughly enjoy my competitive urges, although they mostly manifest in my work. I am not sure if you would call it going for the trophy but I know I can achieve where others have failed. Their failure seems to drive me to success and I will have my own way. This is not so much in my relationships, but certainly when I am working.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mary continued, “There are many stories in my life that I could relate that describe how I demonstrate my warrior spirit. I am not physically competitive at all, but if someone wants to challenge me to a fight then I will fight and enjoy it and I am a nasty player. I am also very outspoken and really very indifferent to what anyone thinks about my actions or words. I cannot remember the last time I had regrets when I did or said something driven by my Aries Moon.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy these times, which is not something that I should really tell anyone, and once they are over I always ask myself should I have done anything differently and my conclusion is always the same. The answer is always no.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She concluded, “I know there are many people that probably dislike me, but equally I know there are those that have a lot of respect for me even if they do dislike me. In summary, I do feel the conflict and I do enjoy it.” That makes me sound terrible but it’s the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can certainly relate to Mary’s feelings. When I shared with a female friend a very satisfying personal success I enjoyed in negotiating a new car purchase, I felt very uneasy afterward and wrestled with whether I should have “boasted” about the “victory”. Here’s what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I told my friend that because I had refused to back down from the salesman’s initial offers, I eventually got an incredible price on the vehicle and even managed to add some bonus items. I shared that I had been unrelenting and assertive, and that at the end of the deal, the male salesman was sweating profusely and almost in tears. When I recounted the experience, I blurted out how much fun the negotiation was - it was like going to battle, and I absolutely loved it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My husband was not with me when I struck the deal - he had to go to the dealership a few hours later and add his signature to the loan papers. The salesman sought him out and shook his hand saying, “Your wife is the toughest negotiator I’ve ever had!” When my husband told me that the salesman complimented me, I couldn’t stop smiling. It felt so good to unleash my Mars AND to get recognition, if not outright approval. I shared my story with full Aries enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was interesting was that a few hours after I recounted the events, I started to feel embarrassed and concerned that I sounded like some sort of maniac on a big ego trip. I wondered if my female friend thought I was bragging, instead of just being happy because I was feeling the power of Mars flowing through me. I fell into the trap of feeling like I had to apologize for savoring such a thrill from my victory in negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This starkly illustrates what Dr. Tannan said about how women minimize differences with each other and avoid the appearances of superiority. In my unabashedly enthusiastic description of my victory, I was doing what men are accepted for - emphasizing my accomplishment and my feeling of power; and it triggered a programmed response of shame and embarrassment. It threatened to take the fire out my Aries Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These feelings change a pure and wonderful experience to one that is tainted and laced with emotional baggage. For many women, this stops them completely from manifesting their Aries power. Developing an awareness of this pattern of feeling shame and then striving to stop the apologies is certainly in order. In most circumstances, there is no reason women should feel bad about being powerful and expressing Mars assertively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One woman whom I interviewed has Mars in Aries opposite her Sun in Libra. She mentioned that when she was in her 20’s, she went to a female astrologer who told her that competition is associated with “the dark side”. She was affected and stifled by this pronouncement for nearly 20 years. Every time she felt the urge to engage in a contest, she felt bad about her tendencies. It took her until she was 40, just after the transit of Uranus opposite Uranus, to break through this and to gain a new awareness about her drive to compete. She realized that her desire to approach situations as if they were a contest wasn’t to make someone else a “loser”- it sprang from her passion to push herself to a new level of personal excellence. Even if she didn’t win, she benefited from the challenge, from the energy of an inspiring contest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, many women I interviewed said that the negative feedback for their assertive and competitive natures comes mostly from other women. I have a good friend with Moon conjunct Mars in Aries who has constant feedback from women saying that she is intimidating, especially in the business world. She’s always perplexed and frustrated by this because her intention isn’t to intimidate. Her frustration is that in order to make her female colleagues happy, she feels she will have to become “someone else”. She is enormously friendly and outgoing, has a brilliant mind and verbal capacity, yet finds she is frequently not accepted by her own gender.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The vast majority of the women I interviewed not only echoed this sentiment, they also mentioned that they tend to have more close male friends than female.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an eye-opening experience several years ago when I was invited to join a neighborhood Bunko group - all women. Some of them had careers, some were homemakers; and they all were very feminine, in the Venus sort of way. I joined the group because I was told that Bunko was a dice game and that there were prizes to be won. I thought, “great!!”, I love to win prizes. Naturally, I approached the game with the desire and determination to win. I assumed that the other women would want to win also - why else play the game?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, I found that the real purpose of the game was to socialize, connect and share stories. Most of the conversation centered on the women’s children or husbands. They did this while trying to play, which meant ultimately the score was never accurately recorded; and the game was pursued casually and halfheartedly. This was very frustrating to me - I felt like I was an alien from another planet. When I showed the least bit of impatience at having to wait for a story to end before we could continue to play, I would get dirty looks and disapproval; and it was particularly uncomfortable if I corrected the scorekeeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately I had to quit the group. I found that I didn’t enjoy it, and I knew that they were not unhappy that I left. I suppose I should have anticipated this reaction. I continue to learn, since early in life, that my direct and assertive approach doesn’t always win points with other females.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was 10 years old I had a situation with some boy bullies who decided it would be fun to tease me unmercifully because I was shy, very tall and incredibly skinny and gangly. They called me names and tormented me to no end. One day on the playground at school, I knew I couldn’t take it anymore, and I turned and confronted the boys. As they circled around me, taunting in unison, I grabbed the closest boy and hit him hard on the back. He collapsed, gasping for air because I had knocked the wind out of him. I thought he was dying! I was scared and really concerned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After he recovered, I was hauled off to the Principal’s office where I was taken to task for my actions. Word spread through the school and soon I found that almost all the girls were mad at me because the boy I had hit was the most popular guy in our grade. I had humiliated him in front of his friends, and they were never going to forgive me. I was summarily kicked out of the “girl club” because I forcefully defended myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, two girls did stick by my side, and we formed a deep friendship. It’s no surprise that one of them has Sun in Aries and one has Moon in Aries. They understood - at least some part of them did.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Unexpressed Aries Energy Can Turn Into Anger&lt;/h5&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Barbara Ybarra, an astrologer in California, has Moon in Aries. She wrote to me with a very insightful idea - linking unexpressed Mars-type energy to Volcanos and the formation of lava tubes. She was responding to my asking her if she felt comfortable using her assertive, warrior energy. She said, “In a Volcano, if a fire burns underneath and gets big enough, it cannot be  easily controlled.  Previously, the Volcano “Kilauea” has used various lava tubes to vent the molten lava, but now there is so much heat and fire that it is threatening to come out the top as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s hard to look at how women experience their strong Aries planets without asking about the changes that women have gone through in society.  My mother also has Moon in Aries (conjunct Uranus), and she has Mars in Scorpio (and also Pluto square Sun)...so you see I grew up with an example of a woman who had energy trouble, and she lived in a more stifling time period.  She made her own lava tubes, venting all over the house, including her husband and children.  Sometimes the fire came out the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember as a child saying I wanted to be a doctor when I grew up.  Then I changed it to architect after awhile.  One day my mother asked me why I chose jobs that were men&#39;s jobs, why not &quot;nurse&quot; or &quot;teacher&quot;.  She talked about whom she hoped I would marry some day.  I was programmed and conditioned, even though I knew that other things were possible.  My warrior spirit and fearless drive was turning to anger, just like it did in her. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the anger that people don&#39;t appreciate, and hidden anger is hard to get rid of.  I think feminine fire energy can be appreciated, but we very rarely see it in its purest form.  We see it when it has to come out, hell or high water...and by that time it is anger”. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The image of a volcano with lava tubes to vent the excess heat is vivid and right on target. Many women create their own symbolic lava tubes so that they can vent their energy and assertive drive. For instance, many will store the aggressiveness and release it in the gym. This, naturally, lets them be less forceful in other areas of life and allows them to fit in with less conflict. Some will channel their Aries energy into keeping a spotless house or being a “supermom” - doing what women traditionally receive approval for, but doing it with the motive to be THE ABSOLUTE BEST.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Others have put a lid on this strong energy completely, suppressing the urge to “win”, afraid to ask for what they want, becoming passive and giving away their power. When Mars is stuffed, an unhealthy situation develops, frequently leading to self-denial or self-destructive tendencies, even depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly, quite a few of the women I interviewed who repressed the Aries assertiveness had allowed it instead to manifest as an eating disorder or other compulsion or addiction. Eventually, when the energy is repressed long enough, and too much heat builds, the lava comes bursting forth. The result is an out-of-control, ugly explosion that usually receives very negative feedback - which then reinforces the urge to stuff it; and then the cycle repeats and the inner heat builds up again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As was the case with my friend “Mary” and Ellen Degeneres, often there is a breakthrough for women at age 40, during the transit of Uranus opposite natal Uranus. Just as Mary had an awakening and was able to release the connection of competition being part of the “dark side”, many women feel a sense of liberation and freedom to express their inner warrior at this time. It’s fascinating that this often coincides with peri-menopause and major hormonal fluctuations. In fact, the number of interviewees who mentioned that menopause helped free the inner warrior was astounding. It’s as if they could finally give themselves permission to just “be themselves” without angst or fear of disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With an awareness of these issues and a resolve to work through them, more Aries women should be able to embrace and honor their strong warrior and trailblazing personalities earlier than mid-life. Here are a few helpful pieces of advice for the young Aries woman:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that there will inevitably be times when circumstances demand a modification or adjustment in how and when your powerful competitive warrior is released. The women with the most harmony and success in comfortably living as an Aries-type all say that they are mindful of when they are around people who will be blown away by, or will push back against, too much assertive drive. These women have created successful strategies to recognize and flow with such a situation - adapting as needed, but not giving away their power or apologizing for their personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Develop a clear awareness of other people’s needs and feelings - we all recognize that this isn’t necessarily the strong point of the Aries temperment. It’s important to know that there’s no way to make everyone happy all the time - however, your mindful intention will radiate out into your aura and ultimately, you won’t ruffle as many feathers...including your own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid comparing yourself to the traditional Venus-type of conventional femininity. Having a Mars-oriented femininity doesn’t make you less of a woman - it’s just that you engage life with a different style. Be clear about who you are. Accept the fact that you thrive on challenge and competition - smile and feel wonderful when you have achieved a new level of personal excellence.

Love the part of you that needs to get right-to-the point in conversations - enjoy the efficiency in this. Relish your dynamic independence and fearlessness. This is so important - when you feel inner acceptance for being strong and gutsy, and when you are willing to moderate your assertiveness when needed, it radiates out into your life energy; and in the end, you will receive more love and support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And always remember - just as you want to be accepted for who you are - with your dynamic, assertive style -strive to afford other women who have a different style, the same spiritual courtesy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt; 

    &lt;b&gt;Chart Data&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tyra Banks&lt;/b&gt; - December 4, 1973 7:13 pm pst Inglewood,CA Rodden rating AA: birth certificate&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ellen Degeneres&lt;/b&gt; - January 26, 1958 3:30 am cst&lt;br&gt;
    Metairie, Louisiana Rodden rating C: caution, no source&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Notes&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Noel Tyl has pioneered the “reigning need” theory related to the Moon sign.&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; Dr. Deborah Tannen, Ph.D. “You Just Don’t Understand”: Women and Men in Conversation 
Ballantine Books 1990&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt; Interesting that when Ellen Degeneres first announced to the world about her sexual orientation
(Feb 1997- on “Opera” and April 1997 when the character on her show “came out”) transiting Jupiter and Uranus were conjunct her Sun in Aquarius, just 4 degrees shy of the Uranus - Uranus opposition (exact Feb 1998)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/05/AppreciatingAriesEnergy/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/05/AppreciatingAriesEnergy/</guid>
        
        <category>none</category>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Aries Point Bloom</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/AriesPointBloom.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
by Kathy Rose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;published in the Mountain Astrologer Magazine&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;float:left; width:25%; margin:0px 15px 10px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/AP_bloom.jpg&quot; /&gt;When we see a rosebud, we
know that contained within it is the
promise of an emergent flower.
Encased in the bud, this future blossom
is not fully formed; it is still
needing development and growth,
awaiting the moment when it will
burst into the light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the bud slowly swells with the
developing flower, we anticipate the
bloom and the expression of beauty
that has been concealed from sight.
When the bud reaches maturity, it
opens; the hidden flower expands into
full view, its petals stretching to the
outside air.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that nature provides
the perfect timing for the bud to
blossom. With the right conditions
of nourishment, temperature, and
sunlight, the flowering plant can’t help
but respond. We observe, in this characteristic
ritual, the outward expression
of what was contained within the
bud, and we’re invited to appreciate
the public stage of development in the
natural growth cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As nature exhibits in the rosebud’s
unfolding, so does astrology provide
the perfect timing for our personal
inner potential to bloom. But instead
of temperature and sunlight combining
to create the right conditions, we
find the planets moving by solar arc to
a special “bloom zone” in the zodiac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symbol of the rosebud’s
opening — the blossoming and public
expression of the flower — can
suggest what happens when a planet
or angle in the horoscope moves to
the Aries Point (AP) by solar arc. The
opening, the blooming, the development
and revelation of the potential within, are all words and phrases that
convey what happens during an AP
solar arc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Aries Point&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is an extremely sensitive and
powerful zone in the zodiac located at
the 0° point of the four cardinal signs —
a special area that relates to high public
visibility. Actually, we could say that the
Aries Point has an orb that starts at 29°
mutable and ends at 1° cardinal. Planets
or angles at the Aries Point in our natal
chart have the potential for high visibility
in life. Sometimes this can suggest
fame or notoriety. The AP indicates
the presence of energy insistence that
pushes a planet or angle into public
view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if the Ascendant in
the natal chart is at the Aries Point,
there is extra potential for one’s outer
personality to be projected into the public
arena. It may be easier for the AP
Ascendant person to be visible and to
get noticed. This can naturally assist the
individual in moving to high levels of
public recognition. Because of this, the
person is often perceived as having a
“big” personality. Astrologer Noel Tyl
has an AP Ascendant at exactly 0°
Cancer. Tyl has a large and powerfully
emotive personality that is easily projected
publicly. When he walks into a
room, everyone feels it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we see Mercury at the AP in
the natal chart, we know that communication
skills (including writing ability)
may well be recognized. There is also
high public visibility suggested in areas
related to the natal houses that Mercury
rules or the house it occupies. Author
J.R.R. Tolkien had natal Mercury at the
AP in Capricorn in the super-creative
5th house in his generally accepted
chart. Tolkien also had natal Saturn at
0° Libra. And isn’t it interesting that his
Lord of the Rings trilogy was built upon
the story’s detailed historical context
and deeply defined character lineage?
We see his AP Saturn and Mercury shining
though the rich language he created
in his powerful fantasy series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The Aries Point offers
the clear potential of
enhanced visibility,
both natally and during
the periods when
planets and angles
move to the 0° cardinal
zone by solar arc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many athletes have planets at  the
AP in their natal chart, including hockey
superstar Wayne Gretzky (Mars), along
with NFL quarterbacks Brett Favre
(Mercury), Tom Brady (Venus), and
Terry Bradshaw (Uranus). Bradshaw’s
AP Uranus makes sense, highlighting
the spontaneity, the urge for adventure,
and the quick thinking needed to be a
great pro quarterback. Tom Brady’s AP
Venus has certainly helped him with
his public appeal; he’s been named as
one of the sexiest male athletes on more
than one occasion. Brett Favre, whose
AP Mercury at 0° Libra is conjunct Uranus
(5° Libra), is noted for being a
smart, intuitive signal caller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You would naturally think that a
famous athlete might have an AP Mars.
But the Mars influence is not limited
to highly visible athletic performance.
I have a client who is a decorated Navy
SEAL, and he has the natal Moon at 0°
Aries. Here, we see the Mars energy
working through the extremely competitive
AP Moon in Aries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivational speaker Tony Robbins
has Jupiter at 29°57’ Sagittarius, just a
few minutes from being exactly at 0°
Capricorn. The AP Jupiter in late Sagittarius
makes so much sense for the type
of work Robbins does. You can’t help
but see and feel his bold enthusiasm
and positivity when he lectures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Aries Point offers the clear
potential of enhanced visibility. This naturally
applies to our natal chart through
our lifetime — &lt;em&gt;and it is also true during
the periods when planets and angles
move to the 0° cardinal zone by solar arc.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Solar Arcs&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we use solar arcs in analysis,
we know that, generally, planets and
angles are moved forward 1 degree per
year of life. I say “generally” because 1
degree = 1 year will work for everyone
until they are 30 years old. After age 30,
we need to consider the month of birth
and make appropriate corrections to the
timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For anyone who is born in March
through September, the 1 year = 1
degree of solar arc timing will start to
break down after 30 years, because the
arc moves a bit slower. Solar arcs are
based on the speed of the Sun, and the
daily motion of the Sun is slower from
March through September.1
 With these
horoscopes, we need to add one more
year to make the calculation work. In
other words, for a planet to move 30
degrees of solar arc, it will take 31 years.
However, for someone born in October
through February, arcing the natal
planets forward 30 degrees will equal 30
years of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important to understand
because, for prediction purposes, we
like to see when the solar arc measurement
is exact. Each month, there is 5
minutes of movement (5 minutes x 12
months = 60 minutes, or 1 degree).
This may sound very technical, but
when you use just your eyes (instead
of the computer) to move the planets
forward by solar arc, you will need to
know this. By 62 years of life, March–
September births will have accumulated
only 60 degrees of movement
forward by solar arc, or 62 years of life
= 60 degrees of arc (it takes an extra 2
years — 1 year per every 30). Whereas
the October–February births remain an
even arc of 60 years of life = 60 degrees
of arc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Looking for the AP Arc&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a point in our horoscope hits
the AP by solar arc, the energy of the
planet or angle moving to that point
blooms and is projected into public view.
If we use the flower analogy — and link
it to astrological timing with solar arcs
— we could say that the “bud” begins
to develop at 28° of the mutable signs,
it swells with growth at 29° mutable,
opens completely and peaks in beauty
or impact at 0° cardinal, and maintains the bloom through the 1° degree cardinal
point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To calculate the age at which a
planet solar arced to the AP, simply
count how many degrees it would take
from its natal position to reach 0° cardinal
(the AP includes all four cardinal
signs). If it is less than 30 degrees,
there’s no need to make a correction. If
it is more than 30 degrees, add an extra
year if the birthday is in March through
September.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s an example, using just my
eyes. My natal Sun is at 29° Scorpio. I
know that if I add 30 degrees of arc to
29° Scorpio, my Sun would be at 29°
Sagittarius. So, at 30 years of age, my
Sun had reached the beginning place
of the AP (29° mutable). If I add one
more degree, the Sun was at 0° Capricorn,
exactly on the AP when I was 31
years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same holds true for any one
of the angles in your chart. Example: A
Midheaven of 2° Virgo would move by
solar arc to the AP at age 28, because if
you add 28 degrees to 2° Virgo, you get
0° Libra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Bloom&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to the power of
solar arcs to the Aries Point through my
studies with Noel Tyl. He pioneered
the powerful idea that when a planet
solar arcs to the AP, the potential of
that planet comes forward and is projected
into public view. When I heard
this, I instantly went to my own chart
to check it out. Using just my eyes, I
moved each planet to the AP and noted
my age. I was astounded! Every single
time a planet hit the AP by solar arc, I
had something significant happen in my
life — something very prominent, very
“public.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Mercury = AP&lt;/b&gt; at age 9-1/2 years: I
tested well in school and was placed
in the gifted class for 4th grade. I had
an intellectual bloom.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Pluto = AP&lt;/b&gt; at age 24: I felt empowered
and started my private practice in
astrology, as well as traveled nationally
to teach intuitive development.
I enjoyed a lot of publicity through radio and newspaper interviews at that
time, too.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;When looking at
Aries Point arcs,
we obviously
must also look
at the whole
picture in the
horoscope.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Sun = AP&lt;/b&gt; at age 31: I got married in
a wonderful ceremony and celebration.
This makes sense because my
natal Sun is in the 7th house of relationships.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Ascendant = AP&lt;/b&gt; (in Cancer): I gave
birth to my first child; the nurturing
part of my personality blossomed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Mars = AP&lt;/b&gt; at age 38: I relocated
from Denver, Colorado to Virginia
Beach. Leaving my birthplace and
the center of my business took a lot
of personal courage!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Uranus and Jupiter = AP&lt;/b&gt; at ages
43 and 44: I was deeply involved in
martial arts, which included a great
deal of sparring. I received my black
belt right when Jupiter moved by
solar arc to 0° Capricorn — a very
meaningful personal achievement
for me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;b&gt;Midheaven and Neptune = AP&lt;/b&gt; (in
2012): I have experienced increased
visibility because of my YouTube videos
(interesting that Neptune rules
video!), and my art business is getting
more recognition.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I said … astounding!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When looking at AP arcs, we obviously
must also look at the whole picture
in the horoscope. We should always
check for strong transits or other solar
arcs that can assist us in our analysis.
There are numerous transits and solar
arcs that will help with success — and in
many cases, high achievement and visibility
will occur without an AP arc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have lots of measurements in
our astrological toolbox — adding the
AP arc is very helpful. Whether this cycle
produces a period of high publicity,
or simply a strong emotional bloom and
an embrace of special empowerment,
there is undeniable development and
personal growth when a planet moves
to the Aries Point by solar arc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Using the AP Arc with Clients&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I work with clients, I consistently
check to see when planets will
move to the AP by solar arc. I know
that if I can open a client’s mind to the
potential of an Aries Point “bloom”
— and the ensuing potential for exposure
offered by this cycle — that person
is then able to create practical strategies
that enhance the incredible growth
opportunity. If we know that a planet
will hit the 0° cardinal point — say, in
three or four years — we are able to set
up better conditions for success, because
we are prepared to cooperate with the
astrology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I often specifically mention to clients
that the “pre-bloom” time frame (planets
or angles at 28° and 29° mutable
by solar arc) signals the “bud phase”
of a growth cycle. There is enormous
background activity and inner development
going on in the last few degrees of
the mutable signs, much of it happening
behind the scenes and hidden from
view. During the bud phase, there exists
an inner process whereby we gradually
gather the resources necessary to build
the inner strength that we need in order
to feel comfortable blossoming and risking
our vulnerabilities by going public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power and energy of the planet
or angle blooms and becomes more visible
when the AP “emergence point” at
0° cardinal is reached. This is an explosion
of potential that has been held
within — a time when our talents or
drive can more easily come into public
view. It’s like stepping out from the
shadows and into a spotlight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can use this bloom cycle strategically
by calculating when the AP will
be activated in the horoscope by solar
arc. Just as we know that the flower will
bloom in springtime due to the molecular
changes triggered during warmer
weather and longer days, we can start
to feel secure in our anticipation that the solar arc to the Aries Point activates a
time of emergence in our life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Blooming in Accord
with Our Life Path&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people whose life plan corresponds
with high public visibility, this
emergence cycle is welcomed and easily
embraced — it resonates. Those who
enjoy the spotlight will more naturally
cooperate with the publicity because
this is their arena, and they willingly
jump in with a hearty smile. With clients
who are extroverted and are comfortable
in high visibility public positions,
I know I can suggest that they should
utilize the AP solar arc strategically to
launch something new, or actively start
a strong marketing campaign or push
for publicity. The typical, driven, “Type
A” personality will certainly have more
potential for grand exposure during an
Aries Point arc, because these individuals
will more readily engage the energy
that this cycle offers. For some, the AP
bloom can help them to step into a new
level of public success, sometimes even
fame. An outward (measurable) level of
achievement frequently results. Here are
some examples of “big blooms” in the
lives of the famous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horoscope for the late superstar
singer Whitney Houston offers a great
illustration of a spectacular Aries Point
bloom. Houston had a cluster of points
that moved by solar arc to the AP in a
three-year period.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; 1983: &lt;b&gt;Pluto = 0° Libra.&lt;/b&gt; This is
when Houston got her big break. She
was offered a fantastic recording
contract. After she signed, she
made her television debut on
The Merv Griffin Show.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; 1984: &lt;b&gt;Mercury = 0° Libra.&lt;/b&gt;
She released her first single,
which became a Top 5
rhythm and blues hit. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; 1985: &lt;b&gt;Mercury = 1°
Libra.&lt;/b&gt; On February 14,
1985, she released her first
album, Whitney Houston.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1986: &lt;b&gt;Ascendant = 0° Aries.&lt;/b&gt;
Houston received four Grammy
nominations, including Album of the Year, and won the award for Best
Pop Vocal Performance. In 1987
(with solar arc Ascendant at 1° Aries),
her album earned a Grammy nomination
for Record of the Year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writer J. K. Rowling has a classic
“rags to riches” story, triggered by an
AP arc. The author’s first book in the
Harry Potter fantasy series was published
in 1997, when Rowling had solar
arc Mercury exactly at 0° Libra. At the
same time, transiting Uranus was opposite
her Sun, and just a few months earlier,
so was transiting Jupiter. What a
fantastic recipe — a “magic potion”
— for sudden success, reward, and visibility
in publishing! Here, we see an
amazing and beautiful synchronicity
with astrological symbolism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine being her astrologer, doing
a consultation with her several years
prior to her big break, and spotting Mercury
moving toward the Aries Point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would have presented a logical
opportunity to suggest that there could
be a decided bloom period in her writing
in 1997. Surely this would be the
time for her astrologer to encourage
her to continue writing, to stay on track
with her aspirations. She had been writing
fantasy stories since she was a child,
and success in pursuing this passion was
one of her dreams. Interestingly, she
came up with the idea for the story of
a young boy attending a school of wizardry
in 1990, when her natal Venus
had solar arced to 0° Libra!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rowling’s spectacular fame and
high public visibility is a classic example
of a bloom that had been in development
for many years, with much hard
work and perseverance leading to success.
She is now a billionaire and is the
United Kingdom’s best-selling author
since records have been kept.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;All charts use Placidus houses and the Mean Node.&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:50%; margin:0px 10px 0px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/chartBenedict.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;i&gt;All charts use Placidus houses and the Mean Node.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vatican City and the
Papal Transition&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another interesting example of the
solar arc Aries Point energy — and one
with incredibly interwoven threads of
AP influence — is drawn from important
current events. On February 11, 2013
came a shocking announcement, catching
many Catholics off guard, that
Pope Benedict XVI was resigning,
abruptly, because of health concerns.
He became the first Pontiff in 600 years
to quit the office. When we look at his
horoscope, we see Uranus oriental at
the Aries Point! (&lt;b&gt;See Chart 1&lt;/b&gt;)
Benedict has the natal signature of
strong individualism and being in the
spotlight due to sudden unexpected
change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s fascinating about
this situation is that, if we consider
the horoscope for Vatican
City (not shown), we find that,
on the very day the announcement
shocked the world, solar
arc (SA) Uranus was at 0°50’
Cancer — sitting right at the
Aries Point. The startling disruption
in Catholic tradition
needed to come forward into the
public eye at this time. Also, we
must notice that the Vatican City
SA Uranus was squaring Pope Benedict’s
natal Uranus in Aries, exactly to
the minute! The suggestion here is that the Vatican City SA Uranus acted as a
trigger to spark Benedict’s natal Uranus,
and we had a public surprise that produced
a powerful shock wave for Catholic
tradition around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story wouldn’t be complete
without mentioning that, just hours after
the announcement of Benedict’s resignation,
lightning (a common Uranus
symbol) struck St. Peter’s dome at the
Vatican.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;When Pope Benedict
announced his resignation, the
Vatican City solar arc Uranus
at 0° Cancer was squaring his
natal Uranus in Aries,
exactly to the minute!&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The signal from SA Uranus at the
Aries Point in the Vatican City horoscope
reflects that the time is ripe for a
pope — and a papal transition — that
may not conform to long-held rules of
tradition, or will bring fresh, new ideas
and patterns to the Church. Immediately
we saw this manifest with the election of
Jorge Mario Bergoglio of Argentina as
the new Pontiff on March 13, 2013. He
is the first pope from the Americas and
the first from the Southern Hemisphere.first to choose the name Francis, in
honor of St. Francis of Assisi.
Pope Francis has pioneered a new
way of doing things — some might even
say a “revolutionary” way. He prefers
to live in simple quarters in the Vatican
instead of moving into the regal papal
apartments; he refused to sit in a chair
on a pedestal while he received the cardinals’
pledges of obedience after his
election (he chose instead to stand at
their same level); and he washed the
feet of two girls during a Holy Thursday
ritual. If you do a Web search of “Pope
Francis breaking tradition,” you will find
many such examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He is also the first Jesuit pope and the first to choose the name Francis, in
honor of St. Francis of Assisi.
Pope Francis has pioneered a new
way of doing things — some might even
say a “revolutionary” way. He prefers
to live in simple quarters in the Vatican
instead of moving into the regal papal
apartments; he refused to sit in a chair
on a pedestal while he received the cardinals’
pledges of obedience after his
election (he chose instead to stand at
their same level); and he washed the
feet of two girls during a Holy Thursday
ritual. If you do a Web search of “Pope
Francis breaking tradition,” you will find
many such examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;All charts use Placidus houses and the Mean Node.&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:50%; margin:0px 10px 0px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/chartFrancis.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;i&gt;All charts use Placidus houses and the Mean Node.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the horoscope for
Pope Francis, we see that SA Mercury
was at 29° Pisces at the time he was
elected! (&lt;b&gt;See Chart 2&lt;/b&gt;) Mercury
rules his 3rd and 12th houses — and
isn’t it interesting that his papal message
revolves around humility and compassion
for the poor? The full bloom (Mercury
reaching 0° Aries by solar arc) will
happen in January 2014, so watch for
an even more profound papal repositioning.
This new pope has something
important to communicate, a message
that will continue to draw public attention
as his SA Mercury blooms.
This is the magnificent bloom of SA
Uranus at the AP in Vatican City’s horoscope
— interwoven with both the outgoing
and incoming popes’ charts — in
full view for all the world to see and for
astrologers to appreciate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Less Visible Blooms&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So often in our culture, we focus
our assessment and approval primarily
on fame or measurable success (accumulation
of wealth, awards, popularity,
etc.). High outward achievement
can be a wonderful thing, something
to be proud of. But how does the AP
bloom manifest for an individual whose
life purpose involves being humble,
quiet, and behind the scenes? What
can we anticipate, for instance, if one
is in the middle of motherhood, giving
total attention and energy to being
of service to the family? Or how do we view an executive assistant who does all
the important administrative work “off
stage” so that a CEO can shine? How
does this cycle manifest for the more
easygoing, introverted, or serviceoriented
personalities?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is critical to consider when
working with clients, especially in how
you present the potential offered during
a powerful solar arc cycle. For greatest
accuracy and benefit in consultations,
we need to adjust our expectations of
how the planet moving to the AP will
manifest, according to the life path, circumstances,
and practical reality of the
client.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the bloom that is experienced
during the solar arc to the AP
isn’t particularly happy or harmonious.
In other words, the process of “opening”
can be difficult, dramatic, occasionally
even painful. If our life path is out
of balance or off track, and we need to
make adjustments in our direction in
order to have more personal fulfillment,
this little gem of a measurement can
provide the push in the right direction.
Following are a few examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients, “Ann” (all client
names are pseudonyms), had been very
unhappy in her marriage for four years,
and we had many consultations where
this issue was discussed. She wanted
to leave her husband and start a new
life, but her long-held pattern of guilt
restrained her. There were many transits
and solar arcs that suggested the divorce
(the fresh start) during the four years
when she was intensely wrestling with
her feelings — some of these transits
and solar arcs were, in fact, very forceful.
With every occurrence, I wondered
whether these cycles would provide the
signal for her to break free. Even though
her frustration increased and her dissatisfaction
grew with each tense aspect,
Ann still couldn’t bring herself to take
action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, when her Sun (ruling
the 4th house) moved by solar arc to
29°30’ Virgo, Ann came in for a consultation
and announced that she was
finally ready to make a decisive move.
Everything was suddenly crystal clear.
Her plan was to get her finances and
records in order so that she could leave
her husband and start a new life within
six months. She had instinctively connected with the rhythm of her Sun moving
toward the 0° Libra point by solar
arc! The inner confidence that she
needed to start a new life was in the
process of coming forward — in public
view — to an irresistible action point.
All the powerful transits in her chart for
the previous four years had prompted
and accelerated the process, but it took
the arrival of the AP bloom cycle for her
to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;We need to adjust
our expectations
of how the planet
moving to the AP
will manifest,
according to
the life path,
circumstances,
and practical reality
of the client.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another client (“Nancy”) had a
cluster of AP solar arcs between the
ages of 31 and 35. During that time, she
was in a pattern of self-sabotage and
underachievement due to alcohol addiction
and substance abuse. When I was
doing research for this article, I asked
Nancy how she experienced the first AP
arc at age 31 (Jupiter = 0° Capricorn
and Mars = 0° Cancer). She instantly
said that it was a period of much inner
growth and that she had felt as though
she were in touch with a “huge ball of
motivating energy” at that time. She
didn’t break through her addictions
then, but she did start to yearn for a
new life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One year later, when Nancy was
32, she had Uranus = AP (0° Libra).
The powerful freedom urges from
Uranus bloomed, and she was compelled
to file for divorce to leave a very
unhealthy marriage. She also started
and, with great intensity, pursued the
process for ending and healing her
addiction patterns. When she was 33
with Ascendant = AP (0° Libra), Nancy said that she was offered an incredible
business opportunity, but she felt intimidated
and not quite ready to trust herself
to follow through for success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now at age 53, she has Neptune =
AP (0° Capricorn), and the growth that
began when she was 31 has been integrated:
She has developed a strong
foundation of healthy habits and is
ready, even eager, to be visible and successful.
She started writing songs when
SA Neptune was in the bud phase (29°
Sagittarius), and she’s now in the process
of releasing her first CD as a singer/
songwriter. The creative energies of
Neptune have blossomed in a beautiful
and fulfilling manifestation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of my female clients attest
that they were able to end a long-term
pattern related to a fear of confrontation
when Mars moved by solar arc to
the AP. Often I hear them say that this
cycle helped them to speak up and draw
appropriate boundaries so that they
didn’t feel victimized anymore. The courageous
energy of Mars “came forward”
and was finally projected out into their
lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have countless examples of clients
who felt a tremendous surge of personal
confidence when their Sun solar arced
to the AP. It’s easy to develop a keyword
system to help understand the natural
thrust of the energy. For instance,
if a woman is in her childbearing years
and is seeking to become pregnant,
Venus = AP is a common signature.
Uranus = AP often carries a powerful
desire to break free, to stir things up,
and sometimes even rebel! Neptune =
AP can produce a beautiful creative or
spiritual bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my clients (“Cynthia”) has
a natal conjunction of Uranus, Pluto,
and the Moon in Virgo sitting right on
her Midheaven. (&lt;b&gt;See Chart 3&lt;/b&gt;, inner
wheel) She had a very controlling
and critical mother who maintained
that being a “good, normal, and
classy” girl was the most important thing
in life. Cynthia was heavily programmed
to dress smartly but conservatively. She
was trained to always be nice and try to
be perfect in every way. This was her
childhood mantra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img alt=&quot;All charts use Placidus houses and the Mean Node.&quot; style=&quot;float:left; width:50%; margin:0px 10px 0px 0px; box-sizing:content-box;&quot; src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/chartCynthia.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;
&lt;i&gt;All charts use Placidus houses and the Mean Node.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cynthia admitted to me that she
had always wanted to have greater
flair in how she dressed. She had yearned her whole life to break free of
her mother’s restrictions and to dress
— to express herself — the way she
wanted. There was an inner desire to
be wild and free, for once! She needed
to accept her Uranus–Pluto conjunction
and powerfully radiate her uniqueness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Cynthia first came in for a
consultation in 2005, I noticed that her
Ascendant would move by solar arc
to the AP in four years (Chart 3, outer
wheel). I could see that, in 2008 (one
year before her Ascendant = AP), she
would have transiting Saturn crossing
her Virgo planets, with transiting Uranus
in opposition. I knew that her identity
could go through a growth period and
that the strong Uranus–Pluto statement
in her horoscope would be triggered. I
suspected that the transits would start
the process, but the Ascendant = AP
would trigger the outer change in her
image and help her to express her
individuality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, she came in for
another session in late 2009, wearing
quirky cowboy boots and a mini dress
with a big floppy sun hat! She was smiling
and genuinely happy that she finally
had the courage to project her originality.
Her Ascendant was shining and
enjoying a beautiful bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here is one more rather classic
but painful example of how the AP solar
arc triggers visibility when your life is not
on track. Actor Charlie Sheen is known
for his high-profile problems with addiction.
He had Neptune = AP exactly (0°
Capricorn) in early 2009. In late 2009,
Sheen was arrested for assaulting his
wife and was charged with felony menacing,
as well as third-degree assault.
His troubles were highly publicized, and
his unhealthy behavior was on display
for all to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next two years, with
Neptune still in orb of the Aries Point,
Sheen’s drug use and bizarre tirades
became much more prominent and, in
January 2011, led to his dismissal from
his hit TV show, Two and a Half Men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sheen’s negative behavior and emotional
meltdowns were extensively covered
by the media and sensationalized
for many months. However, it’s significant
to note that, while he manifested
the behavioral confusion and ego wipeout
often associated with the shadow
side of Neptune, there appears to be a
positive result from the exposure. The
highly visible, acutely public crisis has
apparently helped Sheen to begin new
patterns and get his life, including his
acting career, back on track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Astrological Rhythms that
Signal Growth&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solar arcs to the AP present a special
time for enhanced exposure and
projection of our inner potential and talents.
Our circumstances and life path
will suggest how this may manifest.
Remember, this is not always an indicator
of fame or notoriety; it may just as
well be a signal of quiet but important
personal realization or emotional breakthrough.
The result of these converging
influences is nevertheless a distinct and
determinative bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can plan for the growth that’s
scheduled to occur in our life by simply
looking for the Aries Point solar arc
and understanding that conditions will
be right for some part of our nature to
emerge and become more visible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Informing our clients of the timing
for solar arcs to the AP can be most
helpful — this shines a light of awareness
that provides specific nourishment
for a spectacular bloom. Clients are
grateful for this guidance, because
they can then choose to cooperate
with the cycle in the way that’s right
and “natural” for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we flow with the timing of
the cycles in our horoscope, we enjoy
more success on all levels. We give permission
for significant personal development.
We acknowledge and honor the astrological “rosebuds” in our lives
— the exquisite promise of expansive
growth that is within us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Aries Point Keywords&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun:&lt;/b&gt; Self-awareness and confidence
bloom. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; the
radiance of more inner authority; posture
change (standing up taller, head
held high, shoulders back); shining with
self-assured energy and self-love; often
a time when we move into a position of
leadership; solid ego growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon:&lt;/b&gt; an emotional bloom; acceptance
of personal emotional style and
inner needs. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; a
deeper understanding of what we need
to do in order to feel fulfilled in life;
doing the things that bring us joy —
giving ourselves an emotional gourmet
meal for the soul; often corresponds to
motherhood for women; outward projection
of feeling comfortable with our
emotional style.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mercury:&lt;/b&gt; an intellectual bloom.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; This can be very
helpful to writers and public speakers; a
powerful time for generating new ideas
and calling attention to them; an inner
signal that pushes us to learn something
new or to further our education; communication
blossoms — we give voice
to what has been held within.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Venus:&lt;/b&gt; Beauty and popularity
bloom. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; feeling
attractive and sensual; a highly popular
time socially; growth in romance and
deep relationships with others; fertility;
heightened creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mars:&lt;/b&gt; A new level of courage blossoms.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; Assertive
energy is enhanced; a desire to “fight
back” emerges; often we have the guts
and the drive to take action and make
something happen in our life; there is a
new willingness to take risks; the inner
warrior emerges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jupiter:&lt;/b&gt; A powerful desire for
personal growth blooms. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may
manifest:&lt;/b&gt; self-improvement and a
desire for reward and recognition;
expansion of optimism; strong urge for
adventure and travel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Saturn:&lt;/b&gt; Structure, stability, and
achievement bloom. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt;
a new level of perseverance and
discipline; development of inner authority
and integrity; willingness to work
hard for achievement (follow through);
consistency; necessary patience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Uranus:&lt;/b&gt; Individuality blooms.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; breaking free
from restriction; embracing change;
engaging in high risk and adventure;
allowing oneself to be seen as unique or
eccentric.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Neptune:&lt;/b&gt; Creativity and spirituality
bloom. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; artistic
energy that is channeled productively;
heightened intuition and sensitivity;
stepping into a new understanding of
“flow”; faith and trust understood at a
new level; an opening to deep spiritual
insights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pluto:&lt;/b&gt; Personal empowerment
blooms. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt; expression
of personal power and a willingness
to play in “the big leagues”; leadership
energy emerges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ascendant:&lt;/b&gt; Identity and outer personality
bloom. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt;
special personal magnetism that gets
noticed; confidence with the projection
of identity and self-expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Midheaven:&lt;/b&gt; Career pursuits and
status bloom. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What may manifest:&lt;/b&gt;
significant career growth; publicity;
promotion or receiving a raise; status
change; a special time for personal
achievement and recognition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Chart Data and Sources&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
(in alphabetical order)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;b&gt;Ann&lt;/b&gt;,” August 2, 1961; 12:37 a.m. EDT; Richmond,
VA, USA; AA: birth certificate (BC).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pope Benedict XVI&lt;/b&gt;, April 16, 1927; 4:15 a.m.
MET; Marktl, Germany; AA: BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Terry Bradshaw&lt;/b&gt;, September 12, 1948; 11:10
a.m. CST; Shreveport, LA, USA; DD: Data
(from Penfield) are unconfirmed, and most
Internet sources give September 2; either date
applies, in this case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tom Brady&lt;/b&gt;, August 3, 1977; 11:48 a.m.
PDT; San Mateo, CA, USA; AA: quoted from
employee at Vital Records in San Mateo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;b&gt;Cynthia&lt;/b&gt;,” July 24, 1963; 3:21 p.m. GMD;
London, England; AA: BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Brett Favre&lt;/b&gt;, October 10, 1969; birth time
unknown; Gulfport, MS, USA; X: date without
a time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Pope Francis I&lt;/b&gt;, December 17, 1936; 9:00
p.m. ADT; Buenos Aires, Argentina; AA: BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Wayne Gretzky&lt;/b&gt;, January 26, 1961; 7:45 a.m.
EST; Brantford, Ont., Canada; AA: Brian Clark
quotes him, from hospital birth-card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Whitney Houston&lt;/b&gt;, August 9, 1963; 8:55 p.m.
EDT; Newark, NJ, USA; AA: BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“&lt;b&gt;Nancy&lt;/b&gt;,” December 5, 1958; 7:24 p.m. AHST;
Fairbanks, AK, USA; AA: BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Tony Robbins&lt;/b&gt;, February 29, 1960; 8:10
p.m. PDT; Glendora, CA, USA; A: time given
to author by his seminar organizer in Denver,
from him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;J. K. Rowling&lt;/b&gt;, July 31, 1965; birth time
unknown; Bristol, England; X: date without a
time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Charlie Sheen&lt;/b&gt;, September 3, 1965; 10:48
p.m. EDT; New York, NY, USA; A: Linda Clark
quotes him, he says from birth certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;J.R.R. Tolkien&lt;/b&gt;, January 3, 1892; 10:00 p.m.
LMT; Bloemfontein, South Africa; C: time
unconfirmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Noel Tyl&lt;/b&gt;, December 31, 1936; 3:57 p.m. EST;
West Chester, PA, USA; AA: BC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Vatican City&lt;/b&gt;, June 7, 1929; 11:00 a.m. CET;
Rome, Italy; Nicholas Campion, The Book of
World Horoscopes, The Wessex Astrologer Ltd,
2004, Chart 384.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Note&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
1. Noel Tyl covers solar arc theory and timing
extensively in DVD 6 in The TYL MasterWork
Series, “The Time Dimension,” Rose Productions,
2011 (http://tylmasterwork.com/) and in
his book, Solar Arcs, Llewellyn Publications,
2001.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;© 2013 Kathy Rose – all rights reserved&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kathy Rose&lt;/b&gt; is an astrologer and mandala
artist with an international clientele. She is a
highest-honors graduate of Noel Tyl’s Master’s
Degree Certification Course in Astrology and
is also his teaching associate, as well as the
producer and publisher of the 9-part Tyl MasterWork
DVD series. Celebrating her 30th year
as a professional astrologer, Kathy has recently
created a complete series of zodiac mandalas.
To contact her, telephone: (757) 340-5516;
e-mail: roseastrology@yahoo.com; or visit her
Web site: roseastrology.com.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 04 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/04/AriesPointBloom/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/04/AriesPointBloom/</guid>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Moon Sense</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The following article was published in The Mountain Astrologer Magazine.&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love working with the Moon! Within its silvery light lie the answers to questions about emotions, feelings, needs and intuition. Lunar energy does not intellectualize or reason, instead it knows and comprehends. It is the place to go to connect with the Goddess, the mother energy. It helps us to identify our needs and to nurture them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every month the Moon makes an orbit around the Earth, passing through the twelve signs of the zodiac. As it changes signs every 2 1/2 days, emotional attitudes change, too. This has an impact on your personality, sometimes causing you to feel powerful, at other times sensitive and vulnerable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowing what sign the Moon is in and understanding the emotional orientation of that sign can be very helpful. In fact, certain Moon signs consistently may have more of an impact on you every month than others. Generally speaking, the effects of the Moon are most noticeable when it transits your natal Sun or Moon sign. Strong emotional reactions during that time can indicate a pattern of ignoring your “needs” and not nurturing yourself consistently enough - like putting yourself on a starvation diet emotionally. The Moon’s energy is a reminder to comfort and mother yourself and receive unconditional love from Spirit more often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find consistent vulnerabilities from month-to-month during these transits, take the hint! Attend to your needs! Nourish yourself emotionally on a more regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Likewise if you’ve been consistently feeding yourself gourmet meals emotionally - recognizing the need to “inflow” and receive - you may find the Moon’s transit to your natal Sun and Moon sign a powerful time, when you truly feel “in sync” with your intuition and instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your Sun and Moon sign aren’t the only possible reactive areas in your chart. If you are currently having a solar arc or transit from one of the outer planets (Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune or Pluto), the Moon can trigger emotional activity as well as related events when it passes through the part of your chart being affected. Again, remember, this happens once a month; and in this case it acts like a trigger – stimulating growth that is necessary to get the most from the cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, suppose Uranus is transiting your Midheaven. Most of the time this is a long term cycle, and could take up to a year to complete. Once a month when the Moon transits over your Midheaven, you might feel increased restless and notice that the urge to explore new jobs - or the desire to add adventure and freedom to your career path is stimulated. In this case, each month when the Moon passes over your Midheaven, you will likely examine the issue of whether a new direction is necessary - and you would start to “chip away” at resistance to appropriate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another great way to use lunar energy is to pay attention to the sign the Moon is transiting on a daily basis. As you observe the movement through the twelve signs, you can develop an awareness of how you respond to particular signs and then take whatever measures you need for ensuring a productive experience. You can also become more aware of how these transits affect the public - and observe patterns and changes in the emotional climate and be able to respond accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will probably quickly start to see patterns emerge . The transit of the Moon through certain signs may trigger consistent behavior or feelings every month. It’s important to stay objective though - observing rather than “programming” that you’ll feel or react in a certain way. When you start working with Moon transits, I wouldn’t advise you to first look up the Moon sign and start watching for the “expected” effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the more important spiritual teachings for me is to release the need to be in rigid control of all aspects of life, and instead, trusting, being present in the moment and letting life flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So with that in mind, I suggest you take note of the days that stand out for you personally, then check the Moon. Journal this for a few months. You’ll notice the patterns that reveal themselves. You’ll be able to trust you’re not just projecting an expected result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a personal example, I know that the transit of the Moon in Scorpio is not my best time for staying optimistic and hopeful. Over the years I have experienced this to be true nearly every month this transit happens. My Sun is Scorpio - I am highly attuned to the emotional intensity of this water sign. I am quite aware of this because I am normally a very positive person. I focus on affirmations, meditation and positive prayer nearly every day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the Moon in Scorpio triggers deep introspection and emotional intensity. I brood more during this time, and I often feel like being alone so I can wrestle with my inner fears or other feelings. This moody time points out where I am vulnerable and where I need to grow, and it creates the emotional environment that prompts me to focus on my own spiritual evolution and healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this vulnerability, I take extra care to see myself as a growing and evolving soul. I focus on viewing life as a “quest” instead of a “test” - respecting the fact that the goal is not to be perfect, but instead… to be perfecting. I focus on treating the vulnerabilities that are uncovered as opportunities for growth. This helps me turn the Moon in Scorpio transit into a healing experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I usually experience a sigh of relief when the Moon moves into Sagittarius. There is such a feeling of lightness compared to the emotional intensity of the Scorpio energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another strategy for using the lunar energy is to plan activities that match the energy of the sign the Moon is transiting. For example, I consistently procrastinate doing certain administrative duties. Activities that require a lot of detail and organization (like filing papers or doing taxes), I will avoid as long as possible. So when piles of charts to be filed litter my floor, I watch for a Moon that supports that activity - Virgo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I schedule my administrative chores on a Moon in Virgo day, not only does it mean I get the work done, but I usually get a great sense of fulfillment from accomplishing the chore. For me, this Moon in Virgo strategy works like a charm every time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, will you react the same way to this Moon? It’s not a certainty because it depends on your horoscope and your personality. You might enjoy doing detailed work all the time, so having the Moon in Virgo wouldn’t matter. But just as I know where my weak spots are, you probably know where yours are. It’s helpful to recognize and use the Moon transit that will support your achieving a particular task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously you may not always have the opportunity to schedule activities based on a Moon transit. But when you can, you will feel nourished by an activity that normally feels like a chore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To start using this information you may want to purchase an astrological calendar. There are several good ones to choose from. My personal favorite is Jim Maynard’s Pocket Astrologer - available online or at Metaphysical bookstores.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help you start working with these energy patterns, here is a list of general descriptions for the Moon in each sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Aries&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the Moon is transiting Aries, there is a great deal of physical energy to tap into. It’s a period of ambition, competitiveness and impulsiveness. Initiating new projects, pioneering new paths and acting with courage flow well. Aries craves to do things fast, so impatience and irritation can flare. Beware of the urge to drive aggressively and too fast. If you can find projects where you can work independently and at your own pace you may feel more nurtured by this Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Taurus&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Taurus the energy is steady, solid and persevering. The tendency is to resist change and to protect the status quo. There could be the urge to be more stubborn than usual if pushed for too much change. Generally the Taurus transit works well with practical concerns. Also enjoying good food, hanging out in comfortable surroundings, appreciating beauty and making progress on projects already started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Gemini&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emphasis moves to the intellect with this Mercury ruled sign. Generate new ideas, write, challenge your mind, find an opportunity to communicate. You may feel adaptable and talkative and may even have a hard time staying focused on just one activity. Variety is what nourishes Gemini. This is a time when it’s easier to be objective about emotions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Cancer&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where the Moon feel most at home, so lunar energies are most easily expressed in this sign. Emotions run strong and sensitivity and compassion is high. It’s a good time to be with close friends and family. Baking, gardening and activities related to the home are best accomplished now. Generally it’s a sentimental, nurturing and loving time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Leo&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The energy is outgoing, dramatic and independent during a Leo Moon. Activities that require confidence, enthusiasm, dignity and leadership work well. Being recognized and appreciated also have greater rewards now. Finding outlets to show leadership and encouragement to others can bring a strong sense of satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Virgo&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Detailed tasks are best accomplished now. This is a good time to clean and organize. The energy is inward, precise, perfectionistic and somewhat intellectual. There is strong satisfaction from accomplishment and hard work during a Virgo Moon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Libra&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During a Libra Moon relationships will be important. Connecting with others, communicating and creating harmony are highlighted. It is an excellent time to appreciate beauty and to pursue the arts. The natural flow of energy will move towards socializing and seeking refined activities. It is a good time for teamwork and partnerships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Scorpio&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no way around the fact that Scorpio Moons are intense and passionate. The powerful energies at this time can be channeled into activities such as deep inner healing, transformational work and anything that requires a penetrating focus. Meditation and affirmative prayer are good outlets for this energy. The deep feelings that are stirred up by this Moon can be quite intense. Generally it is not a particularly social time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Sagittarius&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the intensity of Scorpio, this Moon is a breath of fresh air. It’s easy to tap into optimism and positive attitudes. Under the influence of Sagittarius, you might feel particularly friendly, outgoing and adventurous. Promoting ideas, physical activities (sports), spontaneity and sales all flourish now. The need to be free and independent is also a key factor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Capricorn&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The focus now is practicality, ambition and work. Much organization and restructuring can be achieved now. Tasks that require discipline and persistent focus thrive. There is a “bottom line” approach to situations. Feelings and emotions are put on the back burner as achievement and efficiency are more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Aquarius&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The motivating force is intellectual freedom with the Moon in Aquarius. Intellect wins over emotions, and there is often a desire to be unconventional and inventive. Interacting with groups, discussing progressive concepts and exploring the intellect all work well now. Social issues also generate a great deal of interest at this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Moon in Pisces&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagination and a desire to escape the pressures of the mundane world are highlighted during a Pisces Moon. It’s not a particularly good time for hard work, as the energy tends to travel along more creative and mystical lines now. Psychic work, connecting spiritually, enjoying music and creating are natural. This is a highly sensitive and impressionable time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/03/MoonSense/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/03/MoonSense/</guid>
        
        <category>none</category>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Saturn and Guilt</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;by guest astrologer Kathy Rose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kathy Rose is a Highest Honors Graduate of Noel Tyl’s Master’s Degree Certification Program. She has enjoyed a thriving astrological practice for over 20 years, with clients around the world. Her articles have been published by The Mountain Astrologer magazine, and she produces a monthly New Moon Video available at www.roseastrology.com. Kathy can be reached at roseastrology@yahoo.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No one makes you feel inferior (or guilty) without your consent.”
~ Eleanor Roosevelt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my practice, I’ve noticed that Saturn in hard aspect to the Sun or Moon in the natal chart can dramatically signal sensitivity to feeling guilt; to taking on responsibility for things which are out of one’s control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand that when the luminaries are stressed by Saturn contact in the natal chart, there is developmental tension with ego expansion and with the expression of the individual’s reigning needs. Sometimes there are inhibitions to work through - a tight, overly controlled or repressed sense of self is often presented. Because we can anticipate this tension when we see this in a horoscope, we should search for ways to release and redirect the restrictions in development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I see these aspects in a natal chart, I will often say to the client, “How do you see the role guilt played in your early life.” Then I pause… and wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually the flood gates open, and we have a powerful discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I talked with a female client, “Tammy”, who has Sun at 0 Gemini at the MC opposed by Saturn Rx at 29 Scorpio on the IC. When I asked her about the role of guilt in her life, she exclaimed, “I feel guilty about everything!!!!” She continued by admitting that, if anything goes wrong, she always feels it’s her fault; and that she feels responsible for everything, for everyone’s well-being and success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continued to talk, Tammy described a childhood full of physical and verbal abuse. Her father had a rigid and controlling personality - with a highly critical mentality. When she was young, she noticed that if there weren’t total order and perfection in the household, her father would become explosive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition between Saturn and the Sun connected her to the energy of ambition and structured organization - she was wired in this way. Tammy quickly learned that if she handled all the problems of the household, she would avoid abuse, and so would her siblings. Her problem-solving capability around the house became the norm. By automatically assuming responsibility for stepping up and handling things, she had raised the bar for expected behavior. When she didn’t live up to those standards, there was powerful and abusive disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A conditioned response was born - she linked high efficiency, order and a belief that she was responsible for getting everything done, with the &lt;strong&gt;absence&lt;/strong&gt; of disapproval. She also associated making a mistake (or anything less than hyper-efficiency) with abusive punishment. The pattern she developed has been to attempt to ensure that there is order and success in her life AND for everyone with whom she is in relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my conversation with Tammy, we focused on the panic and horrible guilt she feels when she finds herself in a situation where she has no control or isn’t able to fix a problem. She feels it is her absolute responsibility to resolve any such problem. Still, to this day, she is afraid when her world isn’t in perfect order - she fears that a “smack on the head” is right around the corner, cruelly waiting for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another female client, “Kate”, has Saturn conjunct Moon in Capricorn square Sun in Libra. She has a pattern very much like Tammy’s, but without the abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate also related to feeling guilty all the time, especially if she takes time for her personal needs. In the consultation, she admitted being influenced by her Catholic education and by the message, “self pride is no pride”. She was programmed with an unyielding belief that you should never call attention to yourself because that would be selfish and shallow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was further modeled by her Grandmother who lived with the family. The Grandmother lived a life of silent martyrdom - constant work, never resting or taking time for herself. This was in contrast to her mother, a total free spirit who lived in a perpetual state of being overwhelmed and disorganized. Her father was a very regimented military man who was a master at radiating silent disapproval and judgment when there wasn’t order in the household.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kate’s chart, Saturn rules the third house, holding a Capricorn stellium with Saturn-Jupiter-Moon. Her mindset is Capricornian, flowing toward strategic achievement and efficiency; and this is in sync with the reigning need of her Moon - to make things happen and administrate progress. There is a natural orientation to organize and to get things done, and by devotedly following this orientation, she feels rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate learned that she was incredibly capable(!) of taking care of all the disorganization and undone tasks that her mother couldn’t handle, and thus winning the approval from her father - or at least, avoiding the disapproval. She adopted a conditioned pattern of feeling painful self-judgment and guilt, even when there wasn’t the suggestion of disorder. She assumed responsibility for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we had our consultation, Kate was 49 years old and the mother of 5 children. She was exhausted, stressed and emotionally drained from living in a state of chronic guilt-anxiety - fearing that she would not be able to stay on top of the never-ending work in her house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate and Tammy are examples of Saturn’s structured, efficient drive to get things done, to move things forward, and to solve problems by working hard. These traits became exaggerated and ignited by external disapproval. An extreme is set up, and the boundary issue of where responsibility begins and ends emerges. Responsibility runs amuck. –These are examples of painful overachieving in order to avoid guilt and self-judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The opposite reaction&lt;/strong&gt; - underachievement - is also possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another female client - with Sun conjunct Moon in Gemini opposed by Saturn in Sagittarius - manifested the behavior of giving up; there was a pattern of purposeful failure when she felt judgment or disapproval in her early life. The intensity of negativity in her childhood broke her spirit; her self-worth was defeated. Born during the New Moon, she couldn’t find the internal nudge, or drive, that she needed to be able to withstand the harsh energies in her early life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has developed a language of instinctive apology, with “I’m sorry” being interjected many times in every conversation. Her Saturn energy has never risen to the challenge of achievement; instead she proves to herself on a daily basis that she is as “bad” and “unworthy” as she felt her parents projected upon her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of working to &lt;strong&gt;avoid&lt;/strong&gt; the guilt, she embraces it with her underachievement - and her sense of self-sabotage and failure keeps her safe. Her guilt eats away at her self-worth and keeps her stuck in a very dysfunctional pattern, with her feeling as though she doesn’t have the right to take up space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s hyper-achievement with a pervasive over-reaching assumption of responsibility, or purposeful underachievement in order to guarantee disappointment for the sake of staying safe, this guilt syndrome presents a losing battle. It’s an inner conflict where one loses no matter what one does. Guilt is an emotional state produced by thoughts that we have not lived up to our ideal self and could - or “should” - have done better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overcoming such guilt patterns requires a letting go of self-judgment. One needs to create a positive self-image and a mature differentiation of where responsibility (or portions of responsibility) lies. Building self-acceptance is mandatory. We must create new habits that center upon making a CHOICE about how to respond to external disapproval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where therapeutic astrology really shines. If we are confident enough to understand both the structure and the symbolism of guilt as seen through tension from Saturn to the Sun or Moon, we can help our client identify a programmed reaction that controls their behavior and keeps them stuck in negative patterns. We can help them break the circular cycle of guilt and be free from the self-imposed burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people have a deeper awareness of their guilt patterns, they can tear up the permission slip they unconsciously wrote - giving the world their consent for making them feel bad.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/02/SaturnAndGuilt/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/article/2017/02/02/SaturnAndGuilt/</guid>
        
        <category>none</category>
        
        
        <category>article</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Midpointmadness</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Bonus Content Article for TMA Subscribers — Aug./Sept. 2016 Issue&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;by Kathy Rose&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/816TMARoseBC.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tragic mass shooting that recently stunned Orlando, Florida and the rest of the
United States — as well as impacting people in far parts of the world — is still producing shock
waves of sadness and grief for us all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very mindful of the negative effect on our energy field when there is constant focus
on such a tragedy, disaster, or catastrophe. So, my intention with this article is not to continue to
amplify feelings of distress but rather to focus on a meaningful learning opportunity — looking
through the clarifying lens of astrology. In particular, I would like to point out a potent
midpoint pattern involving Mars, Saturn, and Pluto combinations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, let’s take a look at the natal chart of the man identified as the shooter inside the
Pulse nightclub, Omar Mateen. (See &lt;b&gt;Chart 1&lt;/b&gt;, below.) Mateen has a stellium in Scorpio falling in
the 5th house, including the Sun, Mercury retrograde, and Venus retrograde tightly conjunct
Pluto. At first glance, we are instantly able to understand that the shooter was fueled by
emotional energy, and that much of this fixed water intensity is internalized (due to the two
personal planets being retrograde) — supercharged and empowered by the Pluto conjunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been my experience that, when Venus is retrograde in the natal chart, we must
consider an undercurrent of developmental tension, related to social expression and
relationship needs, as an influential part of the person’s life purpose. The degree to which this
may manifest as problematic depends on the complete view of the patterns present in the
horoscope — and of course, on the choices the person makes regarding how to express the natal
energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mateen’s chart — with Pluto conjunct retrograde Venus, which rules the 5th house
(giving and expressing love) — there is a suggestion of challenge and intensity related to the
social and emotional dynamic. So often, Pluto conjunct a personal planet adds “extremes” to the
mix, and here we could say that there is an overabundance of internalized, highly emotional
relationship energy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Natal Mercury retrograde pulls energy inward even more; in Scorpio, the intellectual
process flows from deep feeling and emotion instead of from objective logic. The planet that
symbolizes &lt;i&gt;how a person needs to think and communicate&lt;/i&gt; is internalized and repressed. And since
Mercury is in Scorpio, the thought process could easily move into secretive, clandestine, covert
patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/mateenChart.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quite often, when the two inner personal planets are retrograde, we see a second agenda
swirling under the surface, unknown to others. Symbolically, we could say that Mateen’s 5th
house is similar to an inner emotional volcano, aggressively — even obsessively — churning
beneath the surface with powerful, intensified, and eruptive emotion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tensions reflected in Mateen’s 5th house are reinforced by Mars in Aquarius, ruling
the 11th, in a tight square to the Sun. The energy of giving and receiving love (5th–11th axis) is
powerfully challenged. One more echo of deep hidden emotions is the natal Moon at 29°+ Taurus in the 12th house, opposing the Sun and squaring Mars. A dynamic t-square is formed
that demands our attention when we view this horoscope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing to look at the relationship and sexual energy in the shooter’s natal chart, we
must observe that Neptune is conjunct the Descendant. Neptune on an angle can suggest
unclear energy: &lt;i&gt;“Something is other than it seems.”&lt;/i&gt; There is often confusion or bewilderment that
needs to be worked through as part of the life path, and in this case, it flows into relationships.
Another echo with this same theme is natal Saturn (ruling the 7th and 8th houses) square
Jupiter in Neptune-ruled Pisces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We see a repeating pattern with the planets that rule the houses connected with
sexuality, intimacy, and relationships (5th, 7th, 8th) all involved with challenging aspects.
Again, this suggests that clarifying emotional needs regarding sexuality and relationships is
very much part of the life purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been many news accounts of Mateen’s supposed friends and acquaintances
who came forward and said they felt that he may have been gay. We know that there was
conflict with his religious views — he has been described as a practicing Muslim — and the
issue of whether his alleged homosexuality would be rejected by that community. Mateen
reportedly embraced a radicalized, extreme view of Islam, which projects intense criticism and
condemnation of a lifestyle that is not heterosexual. The symbolism of Neptune on the 7thhouse
cusp is concomitant with the need to hide sexual desires that were not supported by the
important people in his life and the religious views to which he subscribed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Mateen’s chart, there is a clear and powerful statement that sexual and relationship
energy was severely challenged by high developmental tension as part of his life-purpose
theme, and we can assume that this played a part in the choice he made in the location of the
shooting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much more could be said about his horoscope, but now let’s look at the midpoints and
other factors in both his chart and that of the shooting event. There are powerful repeating
patterns involving Mars, Saturn, and Pluto that make a dynamic statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Aries Point Activation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrific mass murder at the Orlando nightclub that catered to LGBT patrons took
place when an important and influential midpoint picture was formed by the transiting planets
at the Aries Point (AP): &lt;b&gt;AP = Saturn/Pluto&lt;/b&gt;. (See &lt;b&gt;Diagram 1&lt;/b&gt;, below. I use the 90° midpoint sort,
which places all the cardinal signs at 0°–29°, the fixed signs at 30°–59°, and the mutable signs at
60°–89°.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/orlandoShootings.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we look at the chart for the event (Chart 2, following page), we can see that the
Aries Point (0° cardinal) was on the angles. I’ve written about the power of the AP before, and
how this zone in the zodiac carries a &lt;i&gt;public projection&lt;/i&gt; dynamic. As I first glanced at the event
chart, my eye naturally could see that the midpoint of transiting Saturn and Pluto that day was
at the AP. Pause for a moment and let that soak into your consciousness. Combine the symbols
of Saturn and Pluto with the AP. What do you feel? It’s a heavy, somber, serious public
statement!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Saturn/Pluto midpoint carries the most challenging energy of all the planetary
combinations, and on the day of the shooting, it was located at 29°38’ Sagittarius — just half a degree from being exactly on the 0° cardinal mark. We could interpret this as the &lt;i&gt;potential for loss
and destruction on a wide public scale&lt;/i&gt;. This powerful midpoint is made even more active because
in the event chart it falls on an angle!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most investigators are now characterizing the shooting as an act of terrorism. The fact
that the midpoint energy of Saturn/Pluto was active at the AP is no surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/orlandoShootingChart.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Saturn and Neptune Connections&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of the event, Neptune and Saturn were exactly square. This is important
because Saturn in Sagittarius brings our awareness to religious issues and the potential for
righteous attachment to strict doctrine or dogma. Neptune in Pisces also calls our attention to
matters of faith&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current transiting Saturn–Neptune square had been activating Mateen’s natal
Saturn–Midheaven (MC) square. The shooter’s Saturn return was in full swing, pushing him to
make big life decisions — this is when we are urged to &lt;i&gt;grow up and pick our path&lt;/i&gt;. The potent
cycle at 29 years of age offers a major course correction, and we make choices about our
commitment to achievement. We know that when Saturn comes back to its natal position, there
is a push to move into a new level of maturity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the pressure from the Saturn return, I believe that the major trigger for
Mateen’s mental/emotional/psychological break was the transit from Neptune to his MC. The
first hit was in March 2016; the final contact would have been in early 2017. Neptune contacting
an angle by transit can offer a spiritual or artistic breakthrough, but it can also intensify
confusion and increase bewilderment, depending on what’s going on in the person’s life. The
increase in emotional distress or disorientation stemming from the Neptune transit may have
felt like a heavy, dense mist, obscuring and reducing the ability to see clearly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If Mateen had homosexual feelings and was programmed to believe that those urges
were evil or sinful — possibly so sinful as to deny him salvation — the Saturn return and
transiting Neptune activation, plus transiting Mars about to station square his natal Mars,
would ignite motivation to do something to release the fog and become clear. He did indeed
make a choice, and it was deadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Continuing to examine the midpoints in the event chart, we see more patterns that
reflect potential violence:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Neptune = Mars/MC&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(confusion and idealism with assertive energy)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Saturn = Mars/MC&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(strategic public aggression, focused protest, or violence)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Mars/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(ego is illuminated through extreme passion, aggression, and force)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Neptune/ASC&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(ego identified with idealism or confusion, possible covert activity)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Saturn/MC&lt;/b&gt; — all are exact by degree! &lt;i&gt;(personal achievement through discipline and hard
work — the need to exert control)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Certainly, the midpoints in the event chart accurately reflect the tragic action, and we
clearly see the repeating pattern with Mars, Saturn, and Pluto.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Omar Mateen’s Natal Midpoints&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we move to a deeper look at the shooter’s natal midpoint picture (Diagram 2,
below), and we see the unmistakable pattern of three heavyweight planets again! Here are the
relevant midpoints in Mateen’s natal chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/mateenMidPoints.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mars = Saturn/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(assertive energy used to release frustration, fighting back with extreme force)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;Sun = Saturn/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(achievement through hard work and discipline).&lt;/i&gt;This is very important to
consider, because transiting Mars in Scorpio was retrograding back to a conjunction with the
natal Sun, further igniting and triggering the killer’s aggressive tendencies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;b&gt;AP = Mars/Pluto&lt;/b&gt; &lt;i&gt;(extreme and forceful energy with public projection). &lt;/i&gt;What a sad thing — to
become famous (AP energy) for a horrible, historic act of extreme violence! This became his
legacy of infamy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Mateen’s Midpoints Activated by Transits&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natal midpoint activation by transiting planets or by Solar Arc directions is important to
consider. When I analyze triggers to key midpoints, I keep the orb very tight. I look for an exact
hit by degree, and the closer to the minute, the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the day of the shooting, we see that the transiting AP = Saturn/Pluto triggered
Mateen’s natal AP = Mars/Pluto. This presents an amazing correlation with the potential for
violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pattern continues with transiting Pluto at 16°49’ Capricorn, igniting Mateen’s natal
Mars/Saturn midpoint, which is 17°01’ Capricorn &lt;i&gt;(assertive energy and discipline come together
with forceful projection — extreme anger and frustration)&lt;/i&gt;. This is again a very challenging and
difficult combination of energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The transiting Sun at 21°42’ Gemini on the day of the shooting was illuminating and
energizing Mateen’s Saturn/Ascendant midpoint, which is 21°24’ Pisces &lt;i&gt;(personal achievement
through hard work and discipline)&lt;/i&gt;. The Sun also triggered his Mars/North Node midpoint &lt;i&gt;(public
aggression or protest)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, there was an exact trigger from transiting Mercury to the natal
Uranus/Pluto midpoint — and also conjunct Mateen’s natal Moon &lt;i&gt;(intense thought activity and
emotion that overturns the status quo – agitated thinking)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more thing: Mateen’s MC and Saturn had moved by Solar Arc to exactly trigger his
natal Jupiter/Pluto midpoint &lt;i&gt;(strategic amplification of personal power)&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again and again, we see the repeating pattern of Mars, Saturn, Pluto combinations
standing out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Media outlets have said that Mateen yearned for a career in law enforcement. He had
applied to the police academy and had been rejected. Over a number of years, he had
reportedly taken and excelled at shooting courses. At the time of the murders, he was working
as a security guard at a gated residential community, which may have fulfilled some part of his
desire — or instead could have underscored a profound sense of underachievement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given the stellium in Scorpio and the midpoints illustrated earlier, this man was wired
to be interested in deep emotional intensity and, perhaps, life issues involving violence. With
appropriate love and support, he could have channeled this into being very skilled at detective
work, criminal investigation, general police work, or the military.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is always a choice as to how we use the energies present in our horoscope. Mateen
had the vocational profile for undercover police work, solving mysteries, and even confronting
violence. Somewhere along the way, he got off track, and a very negative manifestation of his
natal chart was chosen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite probable that his sexual feelings, which may have fueled his confusion, his selfdoubt,
even his rage — feelings in deep conflict with his religious views — helped push him to
make these unfortunate choices. An unresolvable emotional conundrum led to a downward
spiral that triggered the shadow and negative manifestations of all the aforementioned natal
energies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Spectrum of Expression&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I teach astrology, I frequently mention the importance of considering the concept
of &lt;i&gt;spectrum of expression&lt;/i&gt; regarding the natal chart. I believe that two people can be born on the
same day, at the same time and location, and yet express vastly different levels of the planetary
patterns in their natal chart. When we take physical form on the Earth plane, we bring with us
the strengths and vulnerabilities from other incarnations — based on how we’ve chosen to react
and process prior life experiences. It is my belief that we have choice every step of the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the shooter had scheduled an astrology appointment prior to the horrific event, we
would certainly have made note of the obvious challenges and tensions in his horoscope in the
preparation for consultation. However, it is irresponsible to make an absolute judgment, prior
to talking to the client, as to whether these natal challenges might be expressed constructively or
destructively. We must communicate with our clients and listen for details that inform us how
they are living their chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it is incredibly sad that Omar Mateen engaged his natal energies in such an
extreme, negative spectrum of expression. Our ethics as astrologers compel us to remember to
look at all levels of possible manifestation. I believe that we must consider the circumstances in
life development that are specific to the individual before making a declarative evaluation of
natal energies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because a person has a stellium in Scorpio, with Venus retrograde conjunct Pluto,
doesn’t mean there will be powerful emotional or sexual conflict that intensifies and leads to tragedy or violence. The cookbook astrological approach of “this means that” tends to represent
only one tiny portion of possible expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of this very troubled man and a terribly tragic event, we can work backward
and learn from the planetary patterns involving Mars, Saturn, and Pluto that were active that
day. We can absorb the meaningful challenges in Mateen’s natal chart so that we may be more
informed of the potential difficulties if we see similar patterns in our client’s horoscope. Our
goal is to be of service and to help others find a path to the most positive expression of the natal
chart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We must use this knowledge and awareness with wisdom, integrity, and humility. That
is the path of the astrologer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5&gt;Chart Data and Sources&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Omar Mateen&lt;/b&gt;, November 16, 1986; 7:00 p.m. EST; Queens, NY, USA (40°N43’, 73°W52’); AA: birth
certificate published in The New York Times, June 19, 2016.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Orlando Shooting&lt;/b&gt;, June 12, 2016; 2:02 a.m. EDT; Orlando, FL, USA (28°N32’, 81°W23’); news sources
report that the first 911 call came in at 2:02 a.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;center&gt;
© 2016 Kathy Rose – all rights reserved&lt;br clear=&quot;left&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/KathyRose.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;Kathy Rose&lt;/b&gt; is an astrologer with an international clientele. She is a Highest Honors Graduate of Noel Tyl’s
Master’s Degree Certification Course in Astrology and serves as Tyl’s Teaching Associate. Kathy is also the
producer and publisher of the 9-part Tyl MasterWork DVD series, and has developed an appreciative audience
with her popular YouTube channel (roseastrology), featuring more than 100 videos. To contact her, telephone:
(757) 340-5516; e-mail: &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:roseastrology@yahoo.com&quot;&gt;roseastrology@yahoo.com&lt;/a&gt;; or visit her website: &lt;a href=&quot;http://roseastrology.com&quot;&gt;http://roseastrology.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;../../../../../img/articles/816TMARoseBC.pdf&quot;&gt;View pdf version of the file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 01 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/2016/08/01/MidpointMadness/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/2016/08/01/MidpointMadness/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Saturnandguilt</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;by guest astrologer Kathy Rose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Kathy Rose is a Highest Honors Graduate of Noel Tyl’s Master’s Degree Certification Program. She has enjoyed a thriving astrological practice for over 20 years, with clients around the world. Her articles have been published by The Mountain Astrologer magazine, and she produces a monthly New Moon Video available at www.roseastrology.com. Kathy can be reached at roseastrology@yahoo.com&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“No one makes you feel inferior (or guilty) without your consent.”
~ Eleanor Roosevelt&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my practice, I’ve noticed that Saturn in hard aspect to the Sun or Moon in the natal chart can dramatically signal sensitivity to feeling guilt; to taking on responsibility for things which are out of one’s control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We understand that when the luminaries are stressed by Saturn contact in the natal chart, there is developmental tension with ego expansion and with the expression of the individual’s reigning needs. Sometimes there are inhibitions to work through - a tight, overly controlled or repressed sense of self is often presented. Because we can anticipate this tension when we see this in a horoscope, we should search for ways to release and redirect the restrictions in development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I see these aspects in a natal chart, I will often say to the client, “How do you see the role guilt played in your early life.” Then I pause… and wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually the flood gates open, and we have a powerful discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I talked with a female client, “Tammy”, who has Sun at 0 Gemini at the MC opposed by Saturn Rx at 29 Scorpio on the IC. When I asked her about the role of guilt in her life, she exclaimed, “I feel guilty about everything!!!!” She continued by admitting that, if anything goes wrong, she always feels it’s her fault; and that she feels responsible for everything, for everyone’s well-being and success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we continued to talk, Tammy described a childhood full of physical and verbal abuse. Her father had a rigid and controlling personality - with a highly critical mentality. When she was young, she noticed that if there weren’t total order and perfection in the household, her father would become explosive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opposition between Saturn and the Sun connected her to the energy of ambition and structured organization - she was wired in this way. Tammy quickly learned that if she handled all the problems of the household, she would avoid abuse, and so would her siblings. Her problem-solving capability around the house became the norm. By automatically assuming responsibility for stepping up and handling things, she had raised the bar for expected behavior. When she didn’t live up to those standards, there was powerful and abusive disapproval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A conditioned response was born - she linked high efficiency, order and a belief that she was responsible for getting everything done, with the &lt;strong&gt;absence&lt;/strong&gt; of disapproval. She also associated making a mistake (or anything less than hyper-efficiency) with abusive punishment. The pattern she developed has been to attempt to ensure that there is order and success in her life AND for everyone with whom she is in relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my conversation with Tammy, we focused on the panic and horrible guilt she feels when she finds herself in a situation where she has no control or isn’t able to fix a problem. She feels it is her absolute responsibility to resolve any such problem. Still, to this day, she is afraid when her world isn’t in perfect order - she fears that a “smack on the head” is right around the corner, cruelly waiting for her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another female client, “Kate”, has Saturn conjunct Moon in Capricorn square Sun in Libra. She has a pattern very much like Tammy’s, but without the abuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate also related to feeling guilty all the time, especially if she takes time for her personal needs. In the consultation, she admitted being influenced by her Catholic education and by the message, “self pride is no pride”. She was programmed with an unyielding belief that you should never call attention to yourself because that would be selfish and shallow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was further modeled by her Grandmother who lived with the family. The Grandmother lived a life of silent martyrdom - constant work, never resting or taking time for herself. This was in contrast to her mother, a total free spirit who lived in a perpetual state of being overwhelmed and disorganized. Her father was a very regimented military man who was a master at radiating silent disapproval and judgment when there wasn’t order in the household.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Kate’s chart, Saturn rules the third house, holding a Capricorn stellium with Saturn-Jupiter-Moon. Her mindset is Capricornian, flowing toward strategic achievement and efficiency; and this is in sync with the reigning need of her Moon - to make things happen and administrate progress. There is a natural orientation to organize and to get things done, and by devotedly following this orientation, she feels rewarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate learned that she was incredibly capable(!) of taking care of all the disorganization and undone tasks that her mother couldn’t handle, and thus winning the approval from her father - or at least, avoiding the disapproval. She adopted a conditioned pattern of feeling painful self-judgment and guilt, even when there wasn’t the suggestion of disorder. She assumed responsibility for everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we had our consultation, Kate was 49 years old and the mother of 5 children. She was exhausted, stressed and emotionally drained from living in a state of chronic guilt-anxiety - fearing that she would not be able to stay on top of the never-ending work in her house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kate and Tammy are examples of Saturn’s structured, efficient drive to get things done, to move things forward, and to solve problems by working hard. These traits became exaggerated and ignited by external disapproval. An extreme is set up, and the boundary issue of where responsibility begins and ends emerges. Responsibility runs amuck. –These are examples of painful overachieving in order to avoid guilt and self-judgment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The opposite reaction&lt;/strong&gt; - underachievement - is also possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another female client - with Sun conjunct Moon in Gemini opposed by Saturn in Sagittarius - manifested the behavior of giving up; there was a pattern of purposeful failure when she felt judgment or disapproval in her early life. The intensity of negativity in her childhood broke her spirit; her self-worth was defeated. Born during the New Moon, she couldn’t find the internal nudge, or drive, that she needed to be able to withstand the harsh energies in her early life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She has developed a language of instinctive apology, with “I’m sorry” being interjected many times in every conversation. Her Saturn energy has never risen to the challenge of achievement; instead she proves to herself on a daily basis that she is as “bad” and “unworthy” as she felt her parents projected upon her.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of working to &lt;strong&gt;avoid&lt;/strong&gt; the guilt, she embraces it with her underachievement - and her sense of self-sabotage and failure keeps her safe. Her guilt eats away at her self-worth and keeps her stuck in a very dysfunctional pattern, with her feeling as though she doesn’t have the right to take up space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it’s hyper-achievement with a pervasive over-reaching assumption of responsibility, or purposeful underachievement in order to guarantee disappointment for the sake of staying safe, this guilt syndrome presents a losing battle. It’s an inner conflict where one loses no matter what one does. Guilt is an emotional state produced by thoughts that we have not lived up to our ideal self and could - or “should” - have done better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overcoming such guilt patterns requires a letting go of self-judgment. One needs to create a positive self-image and a mature differentiation of where responsibility (or portions of responsibility) lies. Building self-acceptance is mandatory. We must create new habits that center upon making a CHOICE about how to respond to external disapproval.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where therapeutic astrology really shines. If we are confident enough to understand both the structure and the symbolism of guilt as seen through tension from Saturn to the Sun or Moon, we can help our client identify a programmed reaction that controls their behavior and keeps them stuck in negative patterns. We can help them break the circular cycle of guilt and be free from the self-imposed burdens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people have a deeper awareness of their guilt patterns, they can tear up the permission slip they unconsciously wrote - giving the world their consent for making them feel bad.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>https://y7kim.github.io/rose/2016/05/04/SaturnAndGuilt/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://y7kim.github.io/rose/2016/05/04/SaturnAndGuilt/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
